<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages>
<!-- SAND2023-10095O -->

<!-- Potential additional topics to include:
  - How statistical significance tests are applied when (trying to) fit a peak
  - ...
-->

  <message id="intro">
    These are questions users have asked, or things that have been noticed to cause issues 
    or mis-understandings while using <code>InterSpec</code>.<br />
    <br />
    If you have any questions, something is harder than it seems it should be, are having difficulties, 
    or would like to request features or report a bug, please email: 
    <div style="text-align: center; font-size: larger; margin-top: 5px;"><a href="mailto:InterSpec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a></div>
  </message>

  <message id="warm-start" title="Remarks for coming from other spectroscopy software">
    <p>
      If you are familiar with another spectral analysis package, please, you will have to 
      switch your mental model of how the analysis procedure is done while using InterSpec.<br />      
      But hopefully you will find the methodology in <code>InterSpec</code> intuitive.<br />
      <br />
      The most common use of <code>InterSpec</code> for the primary developer is to analyze field-collected
      spectra from a wide variety of detection systems and locations, where the source isotopes, shielding, age, 
      and other information is frequently not known.  Thus <code>InterSpec</code> focusses on flexible interactive 
      analysis, with supporting tools to enable this, and to help assist in answering relevant questions for 
      situational assessment related to the radiation data.<br />
      <code>InterSpec</code> does not focus on analyzing repetitive measurements, or creating formal reports, 
      or using a fixed methodology, but it does try to make common operations fast and easy.

      <br />
      A few notable mental-model differences between <code>InterSpec</code> and other software suites are:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        In <code>InterSpec</code>, when you fit a peak (which, the easiest way is by double-clicking where the peak looks to be on the spectrum), 
        you probably also want to assign a nuclide to it peak at the same time.<br />
        The easiest way to do this is if you are showing reference photopeak lines when you fit a peak, the
        association is automatically made.  But after fitting you can still make or change the assignment by right-clicking on a peak, 
        by using the &quot;Peak Editor&quot;, by typing into the &quot;Nuclide&quot; cells of any table listing peak information, 
        or a few other methods.<br />
        Assigning the nuclide ID to peaks enables fitting for source nuclide activity, energy calibration, 
        doing relative efficiency analysis, detector efficiency characterizations, and more.
      </li>

      <li>
        <code>InterSpec</code> does not use user-made nuclide libraries.<br />
        Instead, you assign nuclides to peaks, and you can always choose nuclides from the total ~4000 available nuclides.  
        Or when searching for nuclides to make an identification for a peak, all ~4k nuclides are used.
        If a gamma-ray comes from a progeny nuclide (ex., the 1001 keV gamma from the decay of Pa234m to U234, in the U238 decay chain),
        you assign the peak to the parent nuclide (ex, the 1001 keV peak would be assigned to U238), and <code>InterSpec</code>
        will perform decay calculations to determine the branching ratio of the specific gamma.
        The nuclides assigned to peaks are the nuclides that will be used to fit activities, or perform other operations.
      </li>

      <li>
        Peak fitting is best done manually in <code>InterSpec</code> - e.g., you identifying where the peaks probably are, and then
        tell InterSpec to fit a peak there (e.g., by double-clicking on the spectrum near the peak, etc). 
        This might seem a little tedious at first, but it allows you to carefully perform nuclide-ID as you go (assigning the 
        nuclide to the peak when you fit it), and ensure good fits - the process becomes quite rapid in practice.
        <br />
        If you really want to have peaks automatically fit for you, on the &quot;Peak Manager&quot; tab, 
        there is a &quot;Search for Peaks&quot; button, which if you are showing reference photopeaks, nuclide 
        assignment can be automatically done as well - but care should be taken.

        <div style="border:1px solid black; width: 90%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
          <div style="display: flex; align-content: space-around;">
              <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/auto_peak_search_btn.png" style="height: 175px; max-width: 49.5%;" />
              <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/auto_peak_search_dialog.png" style="height: 175px; max-width: 49.5%;" />
          </div>
          <div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-bottom: 10px">
             (left) Button to perform an automated peak search for all peaks in your foreground spectrum.<br />
             (right) Results of performing an automated search; if you are showing reference photopeak lines, you have the 
             option to asign that nuclide to the peaks, and only keep peaks near reference photopeak lines.
          </div>
        </div>
        There are also options to automatically fit the same peaks from one spectrum to the next; see the &quot;Working with spectra with similar nuclides&quot;
        topic in this document.
      </li>  
      
      <li>
        <code>InterSpec</code> is only for analyzing data - it does not have any acquisition capabilities; this keeps the application 
        from being tied to a particular type of detector, or making assumptions on hardware or performance.  Clearly separating analysis 
        from acquisition also simplifies and clarifies the user interface.
      </li>

      <li>
        For peak-fitting, nuclide ID, energy calibration, isotopic ratios, and a number of other functions,
        no detector response function is necessary.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </message>


  <message id="save-work" title="Saving your work">
    You have a few options for saving your work in <code>InterSpec</code>
    <ul>
      <li>
        You can save the &quot;application state&quot; to an internal application database, by using the <code>Store As...</code> menu option.  
        Most aspects of the application state are stored (the spectrum files displayed, the peaks fit, nuclide identifications, most tools 
        currently open and thier state, etc), so you can pick up where you left off later.  You can also create &quot;tags&quot;
        or snapshots of your work, so you can go back later.
        <br />
        After saving a state, if you load one of its spectrum files later, <code>InterSpec</code> will check its internal database, 
        to see if you've done work on it, and if so, you will be given a chance to pick up where you left off from.
        <br />
        See the <code>data</code> tab in the <code>About InterSpec</code> dialog for where this data lives on your computer 
        (or equivalently <a href="interspec://about/disclaimer">click here</a>).
      </li>
      <li> 
        Exporting the spectra to a <code>N42-2012</code> file, via the  <code>Export File...</code> menu item, will save all the
        peaks you've fit, the nuclide identifications, energy calibration changes, as well as the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; 
        results,  your current detector response function (DRF), &quot;Isotopics from peaks&quot;, &quot;Isotopics by nuclides&quot; 
        results, and a few other things.<br />
        You can then load the <code>N42-2012</code> file later into <code>InterSpec</code>, and pick up where you left off, or 
        have a record of how you got a particular answer.  However, the state of more minor tools like the cross-section or 
        dose calculators will not be saved to the <code>N42-2012</code> file.
      </li>
      <li>
        In the various tools throughout the application, you can export <code>CSV</code>, <code>XML</code>, <code>CALp</code>, or <code>QR-codes</code>, to represent the
        state of that tool.  These files can, a lot of times, be drag-n-dropped back onto the application to use that work.
        For example, the &quot;Peak Manager&quot; tab has a <code>CSV</code> export link; the resulting <code>CSV</code> file can be used with
        other programs, or if you drag-n-drop back on to <code>InterSpec</code>, even with a different but similar spectrum file,
        <code>InterSpec</code> will fit those same peaks.  Similarly with energy calibration and CALp files.  
        The &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool can export an XML file, that you can import later to use the similar setup.
        And the QR-codes also contain URI links that can be used to have <code>InterSpec</code> open up a certain tool, to a certain state 
        (for example, <a href="interspec://decay/chart%3fgrid%3d0%26logy%3d0%26actunits%3dci%26charttype%3dactivity%26timespan%3d20%20d%26nuc%3dI131%26act%3d1%20uCi%26nuc%3dI129%26act%3d1.5%20uCi">this one</a> will open up the decay tool to have I131 and I129 displayed).
      </li>
      <li>
        There is a &quot;Auto store your work&quot; option as well, that stores most of your changes/work to the 
        internal database mentioned above (this happens when you cleanly quit InterSpec), but currently, as of 
        <code>InterSpec</code> v1.0.11, the only way to retrieve this work is by loading the foreground spectrum 
        file again (e.g., by dragging-n-dropping the file onto <code>InterSpec</code>), while the 
        &quot;Check for prev work&quot; option is set to true; you will be prompted if you want to resume
        from your old state.<br />
        However, this method is potentially unreliable, and probably shouldnt be depended on.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </message>


  <message id="orig-file-mod" title="Does the original spectrum file get modified?">
    When you load a spectrum file into <code>InterSpec</code>, it gets read into memory,
    without modifying the original file; the original file is never read, written, 
    or referenced again.
  </message>

  <message id="mult-open-files" title="Having multiple spectrum files open">
    <p>
      When you open a new spectrum file, any previously open spectrum files, and all the work you've done to them 
      (energy calibration, peaks fit, nuclides assigned, activity/shielding fits, etc) stays in memory.
      As shown below, you can switch back-and-forth between open spectrum files, without losing work.
    </p>
    <div style="border:1px solid black; width: 90%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
      <div style="display: flex; align-content: space-around;">
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/changing_spec_files.png" style="max-height: 150px; width: 49.5%;" />
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/spec_meas_manager_1.png" style="max-height: 150px; width: 49.5%;" />
      </div>
      <div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-bottom: 10px">
         (left) Using the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab to change between displaying and working with different spectrum files in memory.<br />
         (right) Using the &quot;Spectrum Manager&quot; (use the <code>Manager...</code> menu item to display) to select which files in memory to display, or to combine or export files.
      </div>
    </div>

    <p>
      When a spectrum file contains multiple samples (for example, both a item of interest, and a background spectrum),
      The peaks you fit are associated with the <em>sample numbers</em> you have displayed as the foreground.
      So if on the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab, you change which samples you have displayed as the foreground,
      your fit peaks will no longer be displayed, and you can fit new peaks for the currently displayed foreground
      samples; if you switch back to the original sample numbers, your original peaks will be displayed again.<br />
      If one or more of your signal peaks coincide with a background peak, you might display the background 
      spectrum as the foreground, fit the peaks in it, and then switch back to your signal spectrum as foreground,
      and the background sample displayed as background, and when you fit for nuclide activity, you will have 
      the option to background-subtract your background peaks from the foreground peaks.
    </p>
    <p>
      The &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot;, detector response function, &quot;Isotopics from peaks&quot;, 
      &quot;Isotopics by nuclides&quot;, and a few other tools states are associated with the foreground spectrum 
      file in memory.  That is, if you change which sample numbers are displayed as foreground in a spectrum
      file, these tools states will not be changed.
    </p>
    <p>These peak associations with <em>sample numbers</em>, as well as energy calibrations, will be preserved
      if you export a spectrum file in the <code>N42-2012</code> format; the various tool states will also be
      saved into the <code>N42</code> file.
    </p>
    <p>
      Having many spectrum files open at once usually doesn't cause any issues; if memory usage of open
      spectrum files gets above about 256 MB, then spectrum files will be unloaded to temporary swap files,
      and seamlessly read back into memory if you change back to displaying them.<br />
      However, there is a <code>Clear Session</code> menu option that will effectively remove
      all spectrum files from memory, and put the user interface back into a fresh state.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="sample-nums-dets" title="Understanding sample numbers and detector names">
    Some radiation detection systems provide output spectrum files that may have multiple 
    samples in them; that is, measurements made at different times. You can select which 
    of these samples are displayed in as the foreground/background/secondary spectrum
    in the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab; you can display individual <em>sample numbers</em>,
    combine multiple sample numbers, and/or specify ranges.
    <br />
    Some systems may have multiple detection elements, whose spectra are separately recorded
    in the spectrum file.  The individual detection elements will be named in <code>InterSpec</code>,
    and you can choose which ones to display in the <b>View</b> &rarr; <b>Detectors</b> menu. 
    The detector names are often specified in the spectrum file, but if not, <code>InterSpec</code>
    will pick default names.
    <br />
    The <em>sample numbers</em>, and detectors you choose to display as the foreground, or background,
    or secondary spectrum, are summed together for display, or fitting peaks to, or whatever.

    <div style="border:1px solid black; width: 90%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
      <div style="display: flex; align-content: center;">
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/sample_dets.png" style="max-height: 250px; max-width: 49.5%;" />
      </div>
      <div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-bottom: 10px">
        The example passthrough spectrum file which has samples 82 through 94 loaded as foreground, 
        samples 1 through 20 as background, and is only displaying two of the eight detectors in the 
        detection system.
      </div>
    </div>

    <p>
      When reading the spectrum file in, if there are multiple detectors, the spectra are usually grouped 
      together according to when the measurements were taken; that is, all spectra for a given <em>sample numbers</em>,
      will <i>usually</i> have the same measurement start time.
    </p>
    <p>
      The set of <em>sample numbers</em> displayed as foreground, is what the peaks that you fit are associated with; the displayed
      detectors (if the measurement system had more than one detector) do not affect the peak associations.  If you fit 
      peaks for a given set of <em>sample numbers</em>, then change the displayed sample numbers, and possibly fit
      other peaks, then change back to the original sample numbers, your original peaks will be displayed.
    </p>
    <p>
      On the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab, you can specify which <em>sample numbers</em> are displayed by manually
      entering the sample numbers, in formats like &quot;1&quot; (only sample 1), &quot;1-5&quot; (samples 1 through 5), 
      &quot;1-3,8,12-20,10&quot; (samples 1 through 3, 8, 12 through 20, and 10).
    </p>
    <p>
      If the data is search-mode or portal data, a time-chart will also be displayed under the spectrum; you can use this time chart
      to select foreground, background, and secondary spectra <em>sample numbers</em>.
      (hint: use the <img src="/InterSpec_resources/images/more_menu_icon.svg" style="display: inline-block; height: 15px;"></img>
      menu in the upper-right of the time chart to help control selection mode).
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="multi-iso-peak" title="Contributions to a peak by multiple isotopes">
    <p>
      In the <code>InterSpec</code> user interface, only a single specific gamma or x-ray from a 
      single nuclides decay chain can be assigned to a fit peak.<br />
      However, it is common that multiple gammas, or x-rays, from the nuclides decay chain may contribute to 
      the fit peak.  Or it could be that a gamma or x-ray from a completely different parent nuclide also
      contributes to the peak.
    </p>
    <p>
      When performing an &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; or &quot;Isotopics from peaks&quot; analysis, there
      is a &quot;<em>Multiple nuclides contribute to peak</em>&quot; option:
      <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/mult_nuc_contrib_cb.png" style="display: block; height: 20px; margin-left: 20px"></img>
      When this option is selected (which is default), the contributions from all gamma and x-rays within 1.25 FWHM of the peak mean, 
      from any nuclide associated with any of the peaks being used, will be included.  This has shown to generally do a good job
      of accounting for interferences.
      <br />
      Typically the nuclide (and hence gamma/x-ray) you assign to a peak is the dominantly contributing source for the 
      peak.  However, occasionally a nuclide may not be the dominant source for any observed photopeak; in these cases, 
      it is fine to pick any of the peaks that the nuclide contributes to, and assign the peak to the nuclide.  Then for 
      that peak, and any other peak the nuclide contributes to, the (expected) amplitudes will all be properly 
      calculated, and include the nuclide in question.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="background-peak-fit" title="Accounting for peaks in the background">
    You can only fit peaks for the currently displayed foreground spectrum; however, if you want to fit the
    peaks for the measurements background spectrum, you can use the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab to display
    the background measurement as the foreground spectrum.  You can then fit peaks, and switch back to showing
    the item-of-interest spectrum as foreground, and the measurements background as the displayed background 
    spectrum.<br />
    Then in &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, and a few other places, you can select the option to subtract 
    the background spectrums peak.  Using this method of fitting the background peaks has the advantage that
    <code>InterSpec</code> will properly account for uncertainties in calculating activities and shielding.  If you
    do a &quot;Hard Background Sub...&quot;, the data variance in each channel is currently lost, and the peak fits
    will have an artificially low statistical uncertainty.
  </message>

  <message id="fit-source-over-background-peaks" title="Background correction of activities">
    Please see the topic immediately above here.
  </message>

  <message id="create-drf" title="Creating detector response functions (DRFs)">
    <code>InterSpec</code> allows importing detector response functions (DRFs) from a 
    few common sources, but you can also use <code>InterSpec</code> to create the DRF
    for you detector.
    <br/>
    Please see
    <a target="_blank" href="https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/#making-a-detector-response-function">https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/#making-a-detector-response-function</a>
    for a description of the process.
  </message>

  <message id="re-using-drfs" title="Re-using detector response functions (DRFs)">
    Once you have a DRF in <code>InterSpec</code>, there are a few ways to re-use them in the future:
    <ul>
      <li>
        When you create a DRF in <code>InterSpec</code>, and you click the &quot;Store/Export...&quot; 
        button, you will be shown:
        <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/drf_save_dialog.png" style="height: 150px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
        You can export the DRF as a <code>CSV</code> file you can latter drag-n-drop back onto <code>InterSpec</code> to
        use, you can choose to save the DRF into <code>InterSpec</code>s internal database, which you can 
        easily pull back up later.  Or if you export the <code>N42-2012</code> file, the DRF will
        be saved in there, for later use.  The quick-reference card will contain a QR-code that 
        has all the DRF information embedded, which you can scan later to use the DRF as well.<br />
        There is also the option to use this DRF automatically any time you load data either from the 
        specific detector, or the same model of detector.
      </li>
      <li>
        <code>InterSpec</code> stores previously used DRFs in its internal database; if you click on the DRF select button, located 
        in various places throughout the application, and looks like:
        <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/drf_select_btn.png" style="height: 20px; display: block; margin-left: 20px" />
        You can select the &quot;Previous&quot; tab, and scroll through the DRFs.<br />
        The interface looks like:
        <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/drf_prev_dialog.png" style="height: 150px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
      </li>
      <li>
        On the footer of the DRF select dialog, shown above, there are options to export a DRF to an XML file, which can later be 
        drag-n-dropped onto <code>InterSpec</code> to use, or you can display a QR-code, which will embed the DRF information
        into the QR-code.  On the QR-code dialog there is also an option to copy a URI, which will look something like
        <code>interspec://drf/specify?CREATED%3d1682954314%...</code>, which you can put into a hyperlink somewhere and click on,
        paste into the address-bar of a web-browser to have your Operating System then open in <code>InterSpec</code>, or 
        you can paste the URI into the dialog created by the <b>Edit</b> &rarr; <b>Enter URL</b> menu item of <code>InterSpec</code>.
      </li>
      <li>
        The DRF is saved to <code>N42-2012</code> spectrum files as well, so if you load the file at a later time, the DRF will 
        automatically be used.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </message>

  <message id="using-default-drfs" title="Using built-in detector response functions (DRFs)">
    <code>InterSpec</code> comes with a number of detector response functions (DRFs) for common handheld 
    radiation detectors; it also comes with a few generic response functions.<br />
    If a radiation detector model can be determined from the spectrum file, and there is a default
    DRF for that model, when you load a spectrum file, the default DRF will also be loaded.<br />
    If the default DRF isnt loaded, or an incorrect DRF is loaded, you can click or tap the 
    detector select icon:

    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/drf_select_btn_empty.png" style="height: 20px; display: block; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 35px;" />
    
    You will then be presented with a dialog, where clicking on the &quot;<b>GADRAS</b>&quot; tab 
    will provide some generic DRF options, or selecting the &quot;<b>Rel. Eff.</b>&quot; tab will 
    presents you with a list of specific detector models to choose from.<br />

    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/drf_select_defaults.png" style="height: 170px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    
    You can click the <img src="/InterSpec_resources/images/plus_min_black.svg" style="display: inline-block; height: 15px;"></img> icon 
    to import more DRFs from files, that you can choose to save so they will also be in this dialog/tab in the future.
  </message>

  <message id="input-spectrum-file-formats" title="Input spectrum file formats that are accepted">
    <code>InterSpec</code> aims to support common spectrum file types produced by commercially available detectors, as
    well as a number of one-off and text based formats.
    <p>
      If you encounter a spectrum file format not supported by <code>InterSpec</code>, please email 
      an example file to <a href="mailto:interspec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a>, along with any
      documentation you may have.<br />
      However, developer availability to implement is very limited, so priority will be given to widely, or 
      strategically used formats.<br />
      You are also welcome to implement support for a spectrum file format to 
      <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/SpecUtils">https://github.com/sandialabs/SpecUtils</a>, for inclusion 
      into <code>InterSpec</code>.
    </p>
    
    <!--
    An incomplete list of file formats accepted are:
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Format</th>
        <th>Remarks</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          ANSI N42.N42
        </td>
        <td>
          see <a target="_blank" href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9264644">here</a>, including many N42-2006 variants, 
          N42-2012 spectrum files, and N42-2020.  Many models of instruments don't strictly adhere to the standard, with 
          <code>InterSpec</code> implementing work-arounds for those files.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>CHN</td>
        <td>A binary, single-spectrum file format used by <em>ORTEC</em> detectors.  
          This format is described by the <em>ORTEC Software File Structure Manual for DOS and Windows® Systems</em>
          PDF that can be found on a web search.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>SPC</td>
        <td>There are floating-point and integer-based binary formats produced by 
          <em>ORTEC</em> and <em>Thermo Fisher Scientific</em> instruments, 
          as well as an ASCII format produced by <em>FLIR/Teledyne</em> and other manufacturers instruments.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>ICD2</td>
        <td>These typically have an extension of &quot;.N42&quot; and contain analysis results; they are related to N42-2006.
           <code>InterSpec</code> reads in a some of these files, when they also contain spectroscopic information.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TXT/CSV</td>
        <td>Many variants of text and CSV, or TSV files are read into <code>InterSpec</code>.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>GR130/135 .dat</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>PCF</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>SPE - IAEA</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>SPE - LSRM</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>PCF - GADRAS</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>CNF - Mirion</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>MPS</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>SPM</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>MCA</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>ORTEC Listmode</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>XML</td>
        <td>Various, including radiacode, MicroRaider, ScanData</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>ARAM</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TKA</td>
        <td>Canberra Toolkit file.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>MultiAct</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>PHD</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>LZS</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>JSON</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>GXML</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td></td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
    </table> 
  -->
  <p>
    <code>InterSpec</code> can export spectra to the following formats: <code>N42-2012</code>, 
    <code>N42-2006</code>, <code>CHN</code>, <code>IAEA</code>, <code>SPE</code>, <code>CSV</code>, 
    <code>TXT</code>, <code>PCF</code>, <code>CNF</code>, <code>SPC</code> (floating-point, integer, and ascii),
     <code>TKA</code>, <code>EXPLORANIUM GR-130/135</code>, self-contained HTML file, QR-codes, and 
     <code>raddata://</code> URIs 
     (see <a target="_blank" href="https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/references/spectrum_in_a_qr_code_uur_latest.pdf">here</a>).
  </p>
  </message>

  <message id="marinelli-meas" title="Using Marinelli Beaker and other fixed geometries">
    <p>
    To determine activities for a Marinelli Beaker, or other fixed geometries where the normal far-field 
    detector response function approximation breaks down (i.e., the distance between the source and 
    detector is less than about three times the largest of the detector and source dimensions), you will
    need a specialized detector response function (DRF).
  </p>

  <p>
    For the Marinelli Beaker case, often times a multi-isotope calibration standard is used to calculate
    the detectors energy-dependent efficiency.  In this case you can use the &quot;Make Detector Response&quot;
    tool to create a DRF.  You can either input a random distance (like 1 meter), and then later when you 
    fit for activity, use this same distance (and usually no shielding), or starting in 
    <code>InterSpec</code> v1.0.12, there is a  &quot;Fixed Geometry&quot; option you can check in the 
    <em>Make Detector Response</em> tool, which  will remove distance inputs both from this tool, as well as 
    from the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool.  
    The &quot;Fixed Geometry&quot; in the <em>Make Detector Response</em> tool is circled below:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/make_drf_fixed_geom.png" style="height: 150px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
  </p>
    
  <p>
    For geometries, such as <em>in-situ</em> soil contamination measurements (e.g., a detector 1 meter off 
    the ground, pointing down), where multi-isotope calibration standards aren't practical to derive the efficiencies, 
    you will need to compute the efficiencies some other way, usually using something like a Monte Carlo method, or a 
    modeling software like 
    <a target="_blank" href="https://www.mirion.com/products/technologies/spectroscopy-scientific-analysis/gamma-spectroscopy/gamma-spectroscopy-software/lab-applications/s573-isocs-calibration-software">Mirion ISOCS</a>.
    <br />
    Starting in <code>InterSpec</code> v1.0.12, you can import the <em>.ecc</em> files produced by ISOCS
    to <code>InterSpec</code>, by dragging and dropping the <em>.ecc</em> file onto <code>InterSpec</code>,
    which will result in a dialog similar to:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/isocs_ecc_import.png" style="height: 150px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
  </p>
    
  <p>
    If some modeling error is acceptable, using &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool with a standard 
    <em>far-field</em> DRF seems to often provide acceptable results; for example, <em>in-situ</em>
    (i.e., detector 1 meter off ground, pointing down) measurement analysis in <code>InterSpec</code> usually 
    agree within 10%, or better, to methods/packages which properly take into account angular dependence of the detector 
    response (at least for energies above around or above a couple hundred keV, lower energies would likely
    have larger errors).  
    But also please note that for very near measurements (i.e., sample less than ~10 cm from detector) cascade summing can become significant, leading 
    to errors of up to 30% or so, just from this effect, which <code>InterSpec</code> does not currently account for.
  </p>
  </message>

  <message id="soil-contamination" title="Determining surface contamination of soil">
    <code>InterSpec</code> can be used to help determine surface contamination, as well as 
    exponentially distributed contamination in soil, using the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool
    by using cylindrical or rectangular geometries and trace-sources.<br/>
    For full information, please see:
    <a target="_blank" href="https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/#soil-contamination-and-trace-sources" style="display: block; margin-left: 25px;">https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/#soil-contamination-and-trace-sources</a>
    <br />
    A limitation is that as of version 1.0.12, <code>InterSpec</code> does not take into account
    the angular dependence of the detector, unless a &quot;Fixed Geometry&quot; DRF is used; that is,
    if you used a Ortec Detective-X to take the measurement, and the default DRF that comes with 
    <code>InterSpec</code>, this effect would not be taken into account. However, results usually 
    agree to well within 10%, or better, of methods/packages which do properly take into account this 
    effect, at least for higher energies.
  </message>

  <message id="out-of-equilibrium" title="Checking if a decay chain is in equilibrium">
    A few possible methods to check the equilibrium status of parent nuclides:
    <ul>
      <li>Using the &quot;Isotopics from peaks&quot; tool, can be a nice way to see that a 
        decay chain is out of equilibrium, or at a significantly different than assumed age,
        because we expect the detection efficiency to be roughly a smooth function
        of energy, and detector response, shielding, or distance is not needed to be known.
        Here is an example of the tool for a out-of-equilibrium Th232 measurement; there 
        is clearly two separate Relative Efficiency curves, which wouldn't be expected 
        for a sample in equilibrium.
        <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/th232_out_of_equilibrium.png" style="max-height: 150px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
      </li>
      <li> The &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool can be used to fit for a parent nuclides
        age, which can give you the time of chemical separation.
      </li>
      <li> The &quot;Reference Photopeak&quot; tool can be used to show lines for the parent nuclide
        at different ages, with a quick visual inspection of relative peak heights, referenced to the 
        photopeak line heights, sometimes indicating obvious discrepancies, or even allowing for rough 
        age estimates.
      </li>
      <li>Normally you assign a peak to the parent nuclide, and then <code>InterSpec</code> will take
        care of performing the decay, and getting the correct branching ratios for the progeny lines.
        However, if instead you assign each peak to the nuclide directly responsible for that gamma
        (e.g., the 2614 keV peak of Th232, would be assigned to Tl208), you can
        then fit for the progeny activities in the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool
        to figure out at which nuclide in the decay chain the interruption began (e.x., you might
        see a change in activities for Ra226 and below, for the U238 decay chain).
      </li>
    </ul>
  </message>

  <message id="decay-chain-assign" title="Assign the parent nuclide to peaks">
    When you assign a source nuclide to a peak (e.g., you are showing reference photopeak 
    lines, and then fit a peak near a line), you normally assign the parent nuclide to it.
    For example, the 2614 keV peak in the Th232 decay series is created by the decay of Tl208,
    however, in <code>InterSpec</code> you would normally assign the 2614 keV peak to Th232 
    (either by showing Th232 reference photopeak lines before fitting, or by typing &quot;Th232&quot;
    into the <em>Nuclide</em> column of any table showing peak information, or by right-clicking on the peak
    and choosing to assign a nuclide).  When you do this,
    <code>InterSpec</code> internally decays Th232 and assigns the specific nuclear transition 
    leading to this gamma, to the peak.<br />
    The major motivation for assigning peaks to the parent isotope, rather than the specific progeny 
    that created it, is to allow accounting for different branching ratios, as the sample ages, or
    to use gamma line intensities from multiple progeny to do things like fit for shielding thicknesses, 
    or types, using differential attenuation.
  </message>

  <message id="default-age" title="Default ages of nuclides">
    Some simple heuristics are used to guess default ages of nuclides, the logic can be found in the
    <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/bbc3d420a80f03a47ec1341909421cf450624571/src/PeakDef.cpp#L3217">PeakDef::defaultDecayTime(...)</a>
    function, but it roughly follows:
    <ul>
      <li>If secular equilibrium can be obtained, will use 10 secular equilibrium half lives, otherwise 7 prompt equilibrium half-lives</li>
      <li>If the above value is less than one half the half-life of the parent nuclide, then 2.5 half-lives of the parent nuclide</li>
      <li>If the nuclide decays to stable children, an age of zero seconds is used</li>
      <li>If nuclide half-life is greater than 100 years, or for any Uranium or Plutonium isotope, an age of 20 years will be used</li>
      <li>If after the above, the value is more than 100 half-lives of the parent nuclide, then 7 half-lives of the parent will be used</li>
    </ul>
  </message>
 
  <message id="livetime-normalization" title="Foreground/background normalization, and how to change">  
    <p>
      When a background or secondary spectrum is displayed, by default it is live-time normalized to the 
      foreground spectrum (e.x., if the background live-time is twice the foreground, then the background spectrum
      amplitude will be divided by 2), so that visually the spectra are compared according to their <em>count-rate</em>.
      The legend on the spectrum will indicate how much the background or secondary spectrum is scaled by, and the 
      shown live-time for the background/secondary spectrum will match that of the foreground; the total counts of
      the background/secondary spectrum shown in the legend will also be scaled by this same factor.
    </p>
    <p>
    You can adjust the normalization factors using either the sliders to the right of the spectra,
    or by manually typing the desired scale factor on the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab, as shown
    cicled in red here:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/normalize_spectra.png" style="max-height: 350px; max-width: 90%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    If you do adjust the normalization away from live-time normalization, the &quot;Normalize&quot;
    button shown above (in lower-right, for the secondary spectrum) will appear, and when clicked will 
    return the normalization to live-time.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="time-chart-display" title="Time-chart display options">
    When displaying search-mode, or portal data in <code>InterSpec</code>, a time-chart will be shown.
    This time-chart can be used to select portions of time to sum and use as foreground/background/secondary, however,
    unless you do this regularly, the keyboard short cuts wont be remembered, so instead you can click the
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/images/more_menu_icon.svg" style="display: inline-block; height: 15px;"></img>
    icon in the upper-right of the time-chart, to show some slightly easier to use modes for selecting or changing 
    time-periods of data to use:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/time_opt_int.png" style="max-height: 150px; max-width: 25%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    <br />
    You can also use the &quot;Filt&quot; tab to filter the energy range that is summed to form the time chart; 
    a normalization range can also be chosen.  For example, choosing to sum between 170 keV and 200 keV, 
    and normalize to energies above 250 keV, will usually make U235 signal really stand out in; in the figure below
    the same source data is used, but using this ratio-ing will make the signal of interest stand out, when
    the original rate-chart did not indicate it.
    <div style="border:1px solid black; width: 90%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
      <div style="display: flex; align-content: space-around;">
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/time_history_full_energy_range.jpg" style="height: 115px; max-width: 49.5%;" />
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/time_history_u235_energy_range.jpg" style="height: 115px; max-width: 49.5%;" />
      </div>
      <div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-bottom: 10px">
         (left) Time history of search data with no energy range filter.<br />
         (right) The same data, but with 170 keV to 190 keV range ratio-ed with 220 keV and above.
      </div>
    </div>
    <br />
    The &quot;Opt&quot; has some options for how the data is plotted; sometimes the &quot;Don't Rebin&quot; can be helpful for
    spotting narrow hot-spots in really long time-history data.<br />
    The &quot;Rel. y-max&quot; can be useful for (de-)emphasizing the gamma or neutron data. 
    The value can be adjusted between 0.04 and 25. Values larger than 1.0 will cause the neutron y-axis range to be that 
    multiple of neutron data range, while not effecting the gamma y-axis range.  Values less than one will do a similar thing for the gamma data.
    Example effects of changing this value are:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/time_char_opt_2.png" style="max-height: 150px; max-width: 65%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/time_char_opt.png" style="max-height: 150px; max-width: 65%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
  </message>

  <message id="energy-cal-quick" title="Overview of performing energy calibrations">
    The easiest way to perform an energy calibration in <code>InterSpec</code> is often 
    to fit one or more photopeaks, assign nuclide to them (and hence a gamma-line energy), and then on the 
    &quot;Energy Calibration&quot; tab select which peaks to use, and
    which coefficient(s) to fit, and click the &quot;Fit Coeffs&quot; button:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/energy_cal_tab.png" style="max-height: 150px; max-width: 65%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    <br />
    The &quot;Energy Calibration&quot; tab has a ton more functionality; see the help topic on the tool (click
    the question mark in the lower-left of the tab) for more information.
    <p>
    You can also use <code>CTRL + ALT</code> (or on macOS, <code>CTRL + OPT</code>), and the left mouse button
    to click-and-drag the spectrum visually to the correct location.
    If you then do this action again, like first on a high energy peak, then on a low energy peak (or vice versa), 
    the dialog that pops up will give you the option to preserve both actions by adjusting both the offset and gain 
    so this way both peaks will remain at the energies you drug them to.
    </p>
    <p>There is also the possibility of inheriting the energy calibration between successive spectra,
      or using a <b>CALp</b> file - see the next topic for more info.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="reuse-energy-cal" title="Re-using energy calibrations">
    There are two options for re-using energy calibration from one spectrum to another.
    <ol>
      <li>If you are displaying a spectrum, but then open another spectrum from the same detector 
        (i.e., same model and serial number), but  its energy calibration is different from the first, 
        <code>InterSpec</code> should ask you if you would like to use the energy calibration from the 
        first file, with the newly loaded one.
      </li>
      <li>Through use of a &quot;<b>CALp</b>&quot; file, described below.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>
      In the lower left-hand corner of the energy calibration tool there are links to export or import
      <b>CALp</b> energy calibration files.
      <b>CALp</b> files contain the current energy calibration information in a simple text format, and
      allow saving commonly used energy calibrations for easy application to other spectrum files.
      They are particularly useful for working with detectors that either do not provide an energy
      calibration, or provide poor energy calibrations.<br />
      Once you have found an energy calibration you would like to use later, simply click/tap the export
      icon shown below, and save the file somewhere convenient on your filesystem.  When you later want
      to re-use that energy calibration with a different spectrum file, simple drag-n-drop the <b>CALp</b>
      file onto <b>InterSpec</b> and that energy calibration will be applied to the new spectrum file.
      
      <div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
        <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/CALp_down_up.png" style="width: 120px; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
        <div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
          Icons to use for exporting or importing <b>CALp</b> energy calibration files.
          You can also drag-n-drop <b>CALp</b> files from your operating systems filesystem onto
          <b>InterSpec</b> to apply the <b>CALp</b> files.
        </div>
      </div>
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="how-drf-model" title="Detector response function modeling">
    <p>
    The default Detector Response Functions (DRFs) in <code>InterSpec</code>
    hold the efficiency, as a function of energy, for a full-energy detection of a gamma
    ray hitting the face of the detector.  The assumption is that the detector is pointing
    at the source, and the gamma rays are approximately parallel by the time they get to the 
    detector; in practice this means the distance between the source and the detector should
    be at least 3 times the largest of the detector or source dimensions.<br/>
    The DRF also holds the detector face diameter (assuming it is circular) so that solid angle 
    corrections can be accurately made.
    </p>
    <p> The DRF may also hold the parameterized FWHM of the detector.  However this information
      is not mandatory (many of the default DRFs that come with <code>InterSpec</code> do not
      include this information), and is only used, if available, as the initial peak 
      width when fitting peaks; but if this information isn't available suitable estimates are
      made anyway, so it usually doesn't result in any difference.
    </p>
    <p> Starting in <code>InterSpec</code> v1.0.12, there is also an option that the DRF
      may be a &quot;Fixed Geometry&quot; DRF.  If this is the case, then the <em>distance</em>
      option will not be available in the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, as it is 
      assumed the DRF already accounts for this, any internal attenuation of the object, and 
      the efficiency of the detector.  Although you can still add additional absorbers into 
      the problem.
    </p>
    <p> The DRF efficiency is internally represented by:
      <ul>
        <li>A set of energy-efficiency pairs, which get interpolated between</li>
        <li>A set of coefficients for the equation:<br />
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<code>eff = exp( c0 + c1*x<sup>1</sup> + c2*x<sup>2</sup> + c3*x<sup>3</sup> + ...)</code>
        </li>
        <li>An arbitrary mathematical formula that can be entered</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Currently <code>InterSpec</code> does not take into account the angular response of detectors.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="how-sum-peaks-handled" title="How are sum-peaks handled?">
    <p>
    When fitting for activity, sum peaks (either random sum, or true-coincidence) are not currently
    accounted for.
    </p>
    <p> If this might be a problem, it is recommended to move the sample 10 cm or greater from the detector
      where true-coincidence (a.k.a. cascade) summing becomes negligible, and/or to reduce dead-time for
      random summing.
    </p>
    <p> The &quot;Reference Photopeak&quot; tab does offer the option to show cascade sums, to help 
      detect these issues; see the circled options below:
      <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/ref_photopeak_cascade_opt.png" style="max-height: 125px; max-width: 85%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="reusing-peaks" title="Working with spectra with similar nuclides">
    If you are working with multiple spectra that you expect to have about the same photopeaks, 
    you can propagate peaks from one spectra to the next in a couple ways:

    <ul>
      <li>On &quot;Peak Manager&quot; tab there is an option to export a <code>CSV</code> file that contains the
        peak information.  If you fit all the relevant peaks, and assign nuclides to them (if desired), on the
        first spectrum, you can then export the <code>CSV</code> file to a location on your computer.<br />
        Then when you load subsequent spectra, you can drag-n-drop the <code>CSV</code> file back onto 
        <code>InterSpec</code>, and you will be given the option to re-fit those same original peaks, with 
        associated nuclides, in the new spectrum.  Amplitudes and continuum will be totally re-fit, using
        the same continuum model and ROI extents you originally used.  The FWHM and peak means will be allowed to 
        vary a little bit to account for small energy calibration or temperature drifts.
      </li>
      <li> There is an option, <b>Help</b> &rarr; <b>Options</b> &rarr; <b>Ask to Propagate Peaks</b>, that when checked,
        and you load a new spectrum from the same detector (same serial number and model), <code>InterSpec</code>
        will then ask you if you want to propagate peaks from the old spectrum to the new one - similar to using the 
        <code>CSV</code> method described above.
      </li>
    </ul>
    
    There is also a feature under development to allow fitting of peaks in a &quot;batch&quot; mode
    using the command-line.  However, there no estimated date of availability for this or other 
    &quot;batch&quot; features.
  </message>

  <message id="peak-area" title="How the peak area is determined">
    <p>
    The peak area reported by <code>InterSpec</code> is actually the Gaussian amplitude that 
    is determined from a non-linear optimization routine.
    By default peaks are modeled as the continuum plus a Gaussian, with the continuum parameterization
    being fit for at the same time as the Gaussian amplitude and width. <br />
    Some software packages first determine the continuum, then after that is determine the Gaussian, 
    or leftover data, area - this is not how <code>InterSpec</code> does it.
    </p>
    <p> If you right-click on a peak, there is an option for a &quot;<b>Peak Editor...</b>&quot;.  
      From this tool you can change the continuum model, or change the peak type to be a 
      &quot;Data Region&quot; peak, so that the reported area will be the data, minus the continuum area.
      There is also a number of other options for customizing the fit of peaks, or assigning nuclides.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="peak-area-uncert" title="How the peak area uncertainty is determined">
    <p>
      The peak area uncertainty is determined during the non-linear optimization when
      fitting for the peaks parameters.  The uncertainties of the parameters being fit
      are determined simultaneously, and taking each other, and correlations/effects,
      between parameters into account.
      The non-linear optimizer does this by varying the parameters being fit, and
      observing the effect on the &chi;<sup>2</sup> of the peak compared to the data.
    </p>
    <p>
     The uncertainties are statistical only, and do not include any systematic effects
     like the peak skew model or continuum models not being correct.  If you want, you can
     manually edit the peak area uncertainty using the &quot;Peak Editor&quot;.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="short-lived-isos" title="Determining short lived isotope activities">
    When the spectrum acquisition time becomes relevant to a nuclides half-life,
    the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; dialog has an option, &quot;Correct for decay during meas.&quot;,
    that is checked by default, and will account for the effects of the nuclide decaying during the dwell.
    The full decay-chain is accounted for, including progeny ingrowth and decay.
  </message>

  <message id="cascade-summing" title="Cascade summing">
    <p>
    <code>InterSpec</code> does not currently account for cascade (e.g., true-coincidence) summing 
    when fitting activities.  If these effects might become significant, it is recommended to 
    measure the sample at 10 cm, or greater, from the detector, if possible.
    </p>
    <p> The &quot;Reference Photopeak&quot; tab does offer the option to show cascade sums, to help 
      detect these issues; see the circled options below:
      <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/ref_photopeak_cascade_opt.png" style="max-height: 125px; max-width: 85%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="nuc-data-origin" title="Nuclear data sources used">
    The nuclear decay data (half-lives, gamma intensities and energies, etc) largely come
    from ENSDF-V, but have significant additional corrections from observations and 
    other data sources.  X-ray data comes from LBNL ToRI database.<br />
    All this information is accessed via the <code>SandiaDecay</code> 
    (<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/SandiaDecay">https://github.com/sandialabs/SandiaDecay</a>)
    library.
    Gamma/x-ray cross-sections also come from ENSDF.<br />
    Reaction data comes from various places, including 
    &quot;<em>Atlas of Gamma-Ray Spectra from the Inelastic Scattering of Reactor Fast Neutrons</em>&quot; (A.M. Demidov <i>et al.</i>), 
    and the &quot;<em>IAEA Prompt Gamma Activation Analysis (PGAA) database</em>&quot;.
  </message>

  <message id="unit-definitions" title="How are units like year, day, etc. are defined">
    The exact definitions used can be found in <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/master/InterSpec/PhysicalUnits.h">PhysicalUnits.h</a>,
    but internally, <code>InterSpec</code> uses millimeters as the basic distance unit, 
    seconds for time, keV for energy, becquerel for activity, and coulomb for charge; all other 
    units are built from these ones.<br />

    Some time unit definitions used, that could be ambiguously defined, are:
    <ul>
      <li>1 day = 24&times;60&times;60 seconds</li>
      <li>1 year = 365.2425 days</li>
      <li>1 month = 1/12 years</li>
    </ul>
  </message>

  <message id="act-mass-conv" title="How to convert from mass to activity">
    The &quot;Units Converter&quot; tool can convert an activity to a mass.<br />
    For example, entering the text 
    <pre style="margin-left: 20px;">10 gram Th232</pre>
    will result in an answer of 
    <pre style="margin-left: 20px;">1.10 uCi</pre>
    This also works in reverse if you enter the activity of a nuclide.
    <br />
    <p>
    The &quot;Nuclide Decay Info&quot; tool also gives the specific activity of nuclides in the 
    &quot;Decay Chain&quot; tab, when you click/tap on a nuclide.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="interspec-arc" title="Software architecture of &lt;code&gt;InterSpec&lt;/code&gt;">
    <p>
    At its heart, <code>InterSpec</code> is a web-app that is rendered to HTML and Javascript,
    with all the <em>business</em> logic written in C++.<br />
    When you run <code>InterSpec</code> as an application (i.e., on Windows, macOS, Linux, iOS, or Android),
    the application creates a &quot;server&quot; that can only be accessed on your computer 
    (i.e., it opens a random high-number port on <code>127.0.0.1</code>), then it opens a window
    that displays a <code>WebView</code> (provided by the OS, except on Linux where 
    <a target="_blank" href="https://www.electronjs.org">Electron</a> is used), and instructs the 
    <code>WebView</code> to connect to the local server.  By default, an additional secret token is 
    also used to ensure only the wanted <code>WebView</code> instance can connect to the localhost 
    server.  Interactions between the GUI and the <em>business</em> logic happen over the
    localhost network (i.e., your computers internal network bus - it all stays on your computer).
    </p>
    <p>This architecture has been a stable way to allow for cross-platform development of 
      <code>InterSpec</code>.  Using HTML/Javascript for the user interface allows targeting
      nearly all device types, with an appreciable amount of code re-use across other 
      projects, while taking advantage of the large ecosystem of HTML and JS tools and libraries.<br />
      Using C++ for the business logic allows efficient computation and memory management, 
      enabling use of richer algorithms, without sacrificing the applications responsiveness.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="data-privacy" title="Information and use privacy">
    <p>
    InterSpec apps built by Sandia National Laboratories, do not collect any personal information,
    and do not send any information off of your device, except for the two user-triggered 
    actions described below.
    </p>

    <p>
      The two instances <code>InterSpec</code> may cause information to be sent off of your device, are:
      <ol>
        <li>When the &quot;Map&quot; tool is used, map tiles will be requested 
          from https://arcgisonline.com.<br /> 
          Users will be warned before these external network requests are made, 
          and there is an option to use your own arcgisonline.com account to request the the map tiles under 
          (see the in-app Map Tools help for more information).<br /> 
          Only tile locations are relayed to the external server; all plotting of 
          radiation data on the map is done locally on your device.<br />
          As far as the primary developer of <code>InterSpec</code> is aware, no information
          about individual map-requests, or an individual persons requests, is available to 
          Sandia National Laboratories.
        </li>
        <li>
          The &quot;External RID&quot; tool can send your radiation data
          to an external server (or executable on your device) to have a 
          nuclide ID performed.<br />
          Users are warned before using this tool, and they must explicitly enter
          the URL of the server to use for the nuclide ID service.<br />
          Sandia National Laboratories provides a freely available server for this 
          service, but the URL is not pre-populated in <code>InterSpec</code> to explicitly 
          ensure the user wants to perform this action, explicitly enables it,
          and is aware of exactly where data will be sent.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>

    <p>
    Additionally, <code>InterSpec</code> locally stores preferences you may change in the app as well as spectra you load, 
    explicitly saved states, and the app state when it is exited. This information does not leave 
    your device, and can be deleted by removing the application data folder in the operating 
    system's standard location for the app 
    (see <b>Help</b> &rarr; <b>About InterSpec...</b> &rarr; <b>Data</b> for this location).
    There is currently no way to merge this data from multiple computers into a single source of information,
    but you can copy this folder from an old computer to a new one to retain all your old information and preferences.
    </p>
    <p>
      Use statistics and diagnostics are not collected by Sandia National Laboratories; we do 
      not know who, or even how many people use <code>InterSpec</code>, or for how much, except as
      can be inferred through support requests to 
      <a href="mailto:InterSpec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a>, or attendance to webinars, or similar.<br />
      However, if you install <code>InterSpec</code> through your operating systems app store 
      (macOS, iOS, and Android), your operating system may report statistics or crash reports
      to your operating system vendor; disabling this is usually a operating system preference, and 
      except for iOS, you can install the app not through the app-store (e.g., side-load on Android).
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="bleeding-edge" title="Bleeding-edge builds of &lt;code&gt;InterSpec&lt;/code&gt;">
    <p>
      An automated build of <code>InterSpec</code> application is available for the Windows platform at:
      <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/releases/tag/bleeding-edge" style="display: block; margin-left: 20px">https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/releases/tag/bleeding-edge</a>
      This build is updated any time code is pushed to the github repository, and the executable is
      able to be successfully built, and some small sanity checks are passed.
    </p>
    <p> This build of <code>InterSpec</code> is compiled completely from publicly available source code
      on the github infrastructure, so you can be sure of what went into making of the executable.<br />
      However, unlike official releases, the executable is not code-signed, meaning 
      antivirus tools, or <code>Windows Defender</code>, may block initial execution of the EXE.
      Usually clicking on the &quot;more info&quot; link of the resulting dialog will allow you
      to bypass this, or you can add an exception in the <code>Windows Defender</code> options.
    </p>
    <p> The primary value of this automated build is that if you report a bug that has
      been fixed in the code, or request a feature that has been implemented, you
      don't need to wait until the next official release to take advantage of it.
    </p>
    <p>If you would like email updates about official releases, please send an email to 
      <a href="mailto:InterSpec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a>, and you will notified 
      of new releases every few months.
    </p>
  </message>
  
  <message id="add-spectra" title="How to add spectra together">
    <p>
      If you want to sum multiple spectra together, that come from different 
      spectrum files: load all spectrum files into <code>InterSpec</code> 
      (e.g., drag-n-drop the files onto <code>InterSpec</code>, one-by-one), 
      then go to the &quot;Spectrum Manager&quot; (<b>InterSpec</b> &rarr; <b>Manager...</b>)
      and select the specific files or samples you would like to sum (hold the <code>CTRL</code>
      key while clicking on records/files, or hold the <code>SHIFT</code> key to select
      a range), then click the &quot;<b>Sum Spectra</b>&quot; button as shown bellow.
      A new in-memory spectrum file will be created at the bottom of the display area, 
      usually named &quot;summed&quot;, that will have a single record.
      <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/manager_sum_spectra.png" style="max-height: 200px; max-width: 85%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    </p>
    <p>
      Another way to potentially do this, if all the samples are in the same original spectrum file,
      is to use the &quot;<b>Spectrum Files</b>&quot; tab to  display all the samples you would like 
      to sum, for example you could enter the text 
      <pre style="margin-left: 20px;">1,3,8-12</pre>
      to sum samples 1, 3, and 8 through 12.  You can now either work with this foreground spectrum
      in the application, or if you use the
      export spectrum file utility (&quot;<b>InterSpec</b>&quot; &rarr; &quot;<b>Export File...</b>&quot;)
      you can choose to export just these displayed samples, and to sum them together (or for formats that 
      allow just a single spectrum, the summing will be forced).
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="back-sub" title="Background subtracting spectra">
    <p>
      There are two ways to perform a channel-by-channel background subtraction:
      <ol>
        <li>The &quot;<b>Background Subtract</b>&quot; option under the &quot;<b>View</b>&quot; 
          menu performs a <em>visual</em> background subtraction on the displayed plot.  No
          actual subtraction happens, and performing operations like fitting peaks are still
          performed on the full-statistics original foreground.  This background-subtraction
          mode is intended to primarily help visualize and inspect data.<br />
          This mode can be turned off by the menu item, &quot;<b>Un-Background Subtract</b>&quot;,
          that will be shown in place of the original menu item.<br />
          Peak continua may show distortions from this background subtraction mode; this is a
          visual artifact of subtracting the varying data from, what would be a smooth line.
        </li>
        <li>
          The &quot;<b>Hard Background Sub...</b>&quot; option under the &quot;<b>View</b>&quot; menu
          performs a channel-by-channel subtraction of the background from the currently displayed 
          foreground.  When this is performed, a new in-memory spectrum file with a single record 
          gets created, and set as the displayed foreground (e.g., you can switch back to the original 
          foreground - it is kept in memory, unchanged).  All further operations are are performed
          on the reduced statistics spectrum, but assuming the Poisson uncertainty of each channel
          is still the square root of its amplitude, which is not correct (but nearly always close-enough).
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>

    <p> When dealing with peaks that may overlap background peaks, you can load the background as a foreground
      and fit all the relevant peaks (you do not need to associate nuclides with them), then load your
      spectrum of interest, and set your background (that now has peaks associated with it), as your background,
      and in the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, and the &quot;Isotopics from peaks&quot;, and other
      tools, a &quot;background subtract&quot; option will become available, which will properly propagate 
      statistical uncertainties; this method of correcting for background peaks is generally preferred 
      by the softwares author, over a &quot;<b>Hard Background Sub...</b>&quot; subtraction - but in practice
      either way should give similar-ish answers.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="isolate-spectra" title="Making a spectrum file with a subset of measurements">
    If you have loaded a spectrum file with many records in it, but you would like to make a 
    spectrum file with a sub-set of the records, there are a couple ways you can do this:
    <ol>
      <li>
        The easiest way is if you use the &quot;<b>Spectrum Files</b>&quot; tab to display 
        a sum of records, for say, the foreground (for example, enter text 
        &quot;<code>1,3,8-12</code>&quot;, for samples 1, 3, and 8 through 12),
        then you use the export spectrum file utility 
        (&quot;<b>InterSpec</b>&quot; &rarr; &quot;<b>Export File...</b>&quot;)
        and choose to export just these displayed samples, not summing them.
      </li>
      <li>
        You can use the &quot;Spectrum Manager&quot; (<b>InterSpec</b> &rarr; <b>Manager...</b>)
        to select the samples you want, and then create a new in-memory spectrum file, and 
        then export it.
      </li>
    </ol>
  </message>

  <message id="unknown-shielding" title="Dealing with unknown shielding around a source">
    The &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool allows you to use a &quot;<em>Generic</em>&quot;
    shielding type that is specified by the atomic number and areal density.<br />
    If you have peaks from the same (parent) nuclide, at multiple energies, you 
    can fit for the effective atomic number.  However, due to the nature of attenuation cross-section
    as a function of atomic number and energy, you really need at least one peak below 300 keV,
    and preferable a few (above 300 keV, the <em>shape</em> of the attenuation, as a function 
    of energy, becomes very similar between elements).<br />
    You can add a generic shielding, or toggle a material shielding to its effective generic shielding equivalent, as shown below:

    <div style="border:1px solid black; width: 90%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
      <div style="display: flex; align-content: space-around;">
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/shielding_toggle.png" style="max-height: 175px; width: 49.5%;" />
          <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/shielding_toggle_generic.png" style="max-height: 175px; width: 49.5%;" />
      </div>
      <div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-bottom: 10px">
         (left) How to add a &quot;<em>Generic</em>&quot; shielding, or toggle a material to its effective generic shielding.<br />
         (right) The option to check to fit for the effective atomic number of the generic shielding.
      </div>
    </div>

    
  </message>

  <message id="timezone" title="How time-zones are handled">
    Time zones are completely ignored by <code>InterSpec</code>.  
    In a spectrum file, if a date/time is specified with a time zone, the time zone component is discarded.
    It was found the usage of time zones was too inconsistent across different detector models and deploying agencies
    to broadly gain anything by using time-zone information.<br />
    The result of this is that if the time is properly tracked by the detection system, then the local time of 
    the detector is what will be displayed to the user in <code>InterSpec</code>, usually.
  </message>

  <message id="move-work" title="Move work to another computer, or archiving work done">
    <p>
      If, after you do all your work (fit peaks, energy calibrate, fit activities, do isotopics, etc), 
      you export your spectrum file to a <code>N42-2012</code> file, all this work will be included in the resulting
      file.<br />
      If some time later you load the <code>N42-2012</code> file, all your peaks will be present - the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot;
      model and solution you found will be displayed if you open that tool, etc.
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>InterSpec</code> also has an internal database you can store your applications state to by going
      to the &quot;<b>InterSpec</b>&quot; &rarr; &quot;<b>Store As...</b>&quot; menu item.  However, this is effectively
      tied to your computer (although you can copy this internal database from an old computer to a new one
      by copying the files in the OS specified application data directory 
      (see <b>Help</b> &rarr; <b>About InterSpec...</b> &rarr; <b>Data</b> for this location)).
    </p>
    <p>
      Most of the tools also offer <code>CSV</code> and/or <em>XML</em> and/or <em>QR-code/URI</em> 
      exports that capture the state of that tool, and which you can usually be re-imported to the 
      tool (or drag-n-drop onto the application).
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="how-compile" title="How to compile &lt;code&gt;InterSpec&lt;/code&gt; from source">
    The <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/tree/master/target/patches">InterSpec/target/patches</a> 
    directory in the code (available at <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec">https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec</a>)
    provides instructions for this.
  </message>

  <message id="se-de-peak-id" title="Assigning single and double escape peak IDs">
    If you are showing reference photopeaks for a nuclide, and you fit a peak in the spectrum
    that is likely a single or double escape peak, it is likely <code>InterSpec</code> will automatically
    recognize this, and associate it, for example, as &quot;<code>S.E 2614.53 keV, Th232&quot;</code> for a 
    peak fit at 2013.14 keV.<br />
    However, if <code>InterSpec</code> doesn't properly catch this, or you want to make the assignment 
    after fitting, you can try right-clicking on the peak (best while showing parent nuclides reference 
    photopeak lines), and going to the &quot;<b>Change Nuclide</b>&quot; sub-menu, and selecting the appropriate ID, as shown below:
    <img src="/InterSpec_resources/static_text/faqs/se_right_click.png" style="max-height: 200px; max-width: 85%; display: block; margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
    <br />
    You can also type something like &quot;<code>2614 keV S.E.</code>&quot; into the &quot;<b>Photopeak</b>&quot; 
    column of any table displaying peak information.
  </message>

  <message id="fit-age" title="Fitting a nuclides age">
    In the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, when you have selected multiple peaks with 
    the same parent nuclide, a &quot;<b>Fit Age</b>&quot; checkbox may appear in the 
    the center table, that you can check to then fit the age.<br />
    If the peaks you selected are all from the same progeny, or there is otherwise no hope to
    fit age, this checkbox may not appear.<br />
    However, please note that often time you <em>may not</em> have the power to fit for the age, 
    or make a good estimate of this.<br />
    Or, your nuclide may be in equilibrium, meaning some random, relatively large age will be fit, with
    usually a large uncertainty value.<br />
    <code>InterSpec</code> does not (currently) protect you well against either of these cases.
  </message>

  <message id="fit-separate" title="Separately fitting nuclides in a spectrum">
    In the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool you have the option to use whichever 
    peaks you would like in a fit.  Usually if you have multiple nuclides, you can fit for 
    all their activities, and the shielding amounts, all at the same time.  However, sometimes
    you may want to first use the peaks for a single isotope, that you have trust in, to first 
    fit for the amount of shielding, then un-select fitting for shielding, and then add in peaks
    for other nuclides, and fit their activities, or ages, or whatever.<br />
    Cases like this tend to be rare, but it can occasionally be useful to do things like this.
  </message>

  <message id="app-state" title="Saving the applications state">
    <p>
    Storing your applications state to <code>InterSpec</code>s internal database 
    (via &quot;<b>InterSpec</b>&quot; &rarr; &quot;<b>Store As...</b>&quot;)
    will store your currently open foreground/background/secondary spectrum files, your work
    (peaks fit, activities, enrichments, etc), and the state of most tools that you
    might have open (<em>Dose Calc</em>, <em>Gamma XS Calc</em>, etc), 
    your current preferences/option, and a few other things.<br />
    Exporting to a <code>N42-2012</code> spectrum file will capture much of your work, but not things like your current 
    preferences, or the state of most tools (the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; and isotopics tools are 
    the notable exceptions that are stored into the <code>N42-2012</code> file).
    </p>
    <p> Storing to the internal database will allow you to save snapshots that you can go back to if you want 
      (ex, if you want to analyze the spectrum using a few different hypothesis).  It will also enable that if
      you later open the same spectrum file, a dialog will pop-up allowing you to pick back up from where you
      previously left off.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="max-file-size" title="Maximum file size that can be opened">
    By default the largest spectrum file that can be opened in the Windows version of <code>InterSpec</code>
    is 512 MB.  However, if you need to open a larger file you can edit the &quot;max-memory-request-size&quot;
    element of the <code>InterSpec\data\config\wt_config_wx.xml</code> file, to increase this
    (there isn't really a hard limit on the size, but the parsing is done in-memory, so really large
    files will eat up your ram).<br />
    You could also try compressing the file into a zip file, and if that is below 512 MB, you can then open it in 
    <code>InterSpec</code>.
  </message>

  <message id="isocs-drf" title="Detector response functions (DRFs) from other programs">
    <p>
      <code>InterSpec</code> accepts detector response functions (DRFs) in a few forms.<br />
      <ul>
        <li>DRFs created using the &quot;Make Detector Response&quot;, in <code>CSV</code>, <code>XML</code>, <code>URI</code>, or <code>QR-code</code> form</li>
        <li>From <a target="_blank" href="https://rsicc.ornl.gov/PackageDetail.aspx?p=GADRAS-DRF-18.8.13&amp;id=P00610&amp;cpu=PCX86&amp;v=04&amp;t=Gamma%20Detector%20Response%20and%20Analysis%20Software–Detector%20Response%20Function.">GADRAS-DRF</a></li>
        <li>In a couple <code>CSV</code>/<code>TSV</code> formats</li>
        <li><code>.ECC</code> files produced by
          <a target="_blank" href="https://www.mirion.com/products/technologies/spectroscopy-scientific-analysis/gamma-spectroscopy/gamma-spectroscopy-software/lab-applications/s573-isocs-calibration-software">Mirion ISOCS</a>
        </li>
        <li>Through directly inputting a mathematical function in the &quot;Detector Response Function Select&quot; tool.</li>
      </ul>
      
      See the <em>help</em> page for the &quot;Detector Response Function Select&quot; tool for more information.
    </p>
  </message>
<!--
  <message id="how-peak-fitter-works" title="How does the peak fitter work.">
    ...
  </message>
-->
  <message id="multi-ref-lines" title="Showing multiple reference photopeak reference lines at once">
    You can show the reference photopeak lines for multiple nuclides and/or reaction at once, by first 
    inputting the first nuclide into the <b>Reference Photopeak</b> tab, then clicking the 
    &quot;<b>Add Another</b>&quot; button and entering your second nuclide, and so on.  <br/>
    You can change the shielding and nuclide age for each nuclide, with the values you enter before 
    clicking the &quot;<b>Add Another</b>&quot; button, being what will be used, independent of what 
    you use for future nuclides added.<br/>
    Each nuclide you add will be normalized to itself; that is, the maximum yield gamma/x-ray line
    for each nuclide will scale to about the top of the spectrum - there is (currently) no way
    to specify a relative scaling between nuclides.
  </message>

  <message id="dist-def" title="How &quot;Distance&quot; is defined for fitting activity">
    In the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, and other places, the distance
    is always defined from the detector face, to the <em>center</em> of the source.<br/>
    <em>Not</em> the edge of the shielding, like if you were measuring with a tape measure.
    That is, if your source is a box, and you measure from the detector face to the surface of the
    box, you will need to add one-half of the boxes depth to this measurement, for the value
    you enter into <code>InterSpec</code>.
  </message>

  <message id="act-line-weighting" title="How activity is weighted between multiple gamma lines">
    In the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool if you use multiple peaks for a parent nuclide,
    the reported activity is a weighted average of all of them, with the weighting being defined by
    the peak area uncertainties (DRF uncertainties will be added in the future - they are currently ignored).
  </message>

  <message id="key-line" title="Is there a key line">
    <p>
      <code>InterSpec</code> does not support the concept of a <em>key-line</em>, like other software use.
      If you want to estimate an activity based off of a single gamma energy, then in the 
      &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool, de-select all other peaks, and de-select any 
      fit options for the shielding, then hit the &quot;Fit Model&quot; button, 
      and you will get the activity of that single peak.
    </p>
    <p>
      The chart on the &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool can be toggled 
      between showing statistical deviations of each peaks, and the amplitude 
      discrepancies of each peak, compared to the weighted average value.  This chart provides 
      a good indication of how consistent each peak estimates activity, and if the
      shielding, DRF, and nuclide age are all modeled well, then the chart will
      show the peaks to be consistent with each other.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="how-make-nuc-library" title="How to make a nuclide library">
    <code>InterSpec</code> does not support the concept of a nuclide library.<br/>
    You assign a nuclide, x-ray, or reaction to peaks, and the
    assignments you make determine which activities can be fit for in the 
    &quot;Activity/Shielding Fit&quot; tool.
  </message>

  <message id="zero-amp-fit" title="Fitting zero-amplitude peaks">
    If you want to fit a low, or zero, amplitude peak, holding the <b>CTRL</b> key, plus dragging 
    over the region of interest (ROI) with the mouse will force a peak to be fit; no statistical 
    significance thresholds are applied, like if you were to double-click on the spectrum.<br/>
    Instead you can also use the &quot;Add...&quot; button on the &quot;Peak Manager&quot;
    tab to force add a peak.
  </message>

  
  <message id="search-profile" title="How the &quot;Profile&quot; ordering is defined when searching for nuclides">
    <p>
      On the &quot;Nuclide Search&quot; tab, when you search on an energy, by default the results
      are ordered by the &quot;<b>Profile</b>&quot; column.<br/>
      You can click on the header of any other column to order the results by that column, but usually
      &quot;<b>Profile</b>&quot; is the best option.
    </p>
    <p>
      Roughly, the &quot;<b>Profile</b>&quot; column is calculated by looking for peaks that would be 
      naively expected from a nuclide, under a few shielding conditions (none, light, heavy) and ages,
      and comparing the observed peaks, to predicted.  If there are extra peaks in the spectrum, no 
      penalty is added, but if a peak that was expected is not observed (e.g., if a peak is predicted 
      between two other peaks that are predicted and observed, but the middle peak is not observed), 
      than a penalty is assessed.  The score also includes a naive evaluation of the relative heights 
      of multiple peaks, compared to expectations.  The peaks used for this evaluation is a combination
      of peaks fit by the user, as well as an automated search of peaks in the spectrum.
    </p>
    <p>
      This weighting is a heuristic that is intended to provide reasonable ordering
      of results from the ~4000 nuclides available in <code>InterSpec</code>, without 
      introducing biases of commonly seen nuclides, or expected half-lives, etc.<br/>
      A downside of trying not to bias things, is that if you search on an energy
      like 2614.53 keV, the top result wont be the common answer of Th232, but instead 
      include results of all the possible nuclides that decay through Tl208 (whose
      decay is the one that results in the 2614.53 keV gamma).  This is intended, because it might be
      critical that you catch U232, or Th228, or Pu236 can all have this line, instead
      of just assuming Th232.<br/>
      In practice the heuristic used seems to work pretty well, given it has no priors 
      injected into its results.  
    </p>
    <p>
      If you would like some priors based on likely encountered nuclides, you can 
      right-click on a peak, and go to the &quot;<b>Change Nuclide</b>&quot;
      sub-menu for suggestions.
    </p>
    <p>The implementation of this scoring method can be found in the 
      <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/b38a80b6ef14a8ea21940fb8fc2558aee8a3aaf1/src/IsotopeSearchByEnergyModel.cpp#L240">profile_weight(...)</a>
      function in the code; the comments in the code clearly indicate how the above procedure 
      was developed through informal, non-rigorous, experimentation, and there seems to 
      be clear room for improvement - feedback is always welcome for any part of <code>InterSpec</code>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="peak-suggestions" title="Where nuclide-suggestions on right-clicks come from">
    When you right-click on a peak, and go to the &quot;<b>Change Nuclide</b>&quot;, menu,
    the suggested nuclides come from a few different places.
    
    <ul>
      <li>The currently displayed reference photopeak lines are checked for energies nearby the peak</li>
      <li>The nuclides of other peaks that have been identified are checked for energies nearby the peak</li>
      <li>A file, 
        <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/master/data/PhotoPeak.lis">PhotoPeak.lis</a>
        is included with <code>InterSpec</code> (the file is originally from 
        <a target="_blank" href="https://rsicc.ornl.gov/PackageDetail.aspx?p=GADRAS-DRF-18.8.13&amp;id=P00610&amp;cpu=PCX86&amp;v=04&amp;t=Gamma%20Detector%20Response%20and%20Analysis%20Software–Detector%20Response%20Function.">GADRAS-DRF</a>)
        which has about 10,000 energies mapped to their likely nuclide, x-ray, or reaction source.
      </li>
      <li>
        A file, 
        <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/master/data/CharacteristicGammas.txt">CharacteristicGammas.txt</a>
        is included with <code>InterSpec</code> (the file is originally from 
        <a target="_blank" href="https://rsicc.ornl.gov/PackageDetail.aspx?p=GADRAS-DRF-18.8.13&amp;id=P00610&amp;cpu=PCX86&amp;v=04&amp;t=Gamma%20Detector%20Response%20and%20Analysis%20Software–Detector%20Response%20Function.">GADRAS-DRF</a>)
        which has about 50 common nuclides with the energies that are characteristic to them.
      </li>
      <li>Single and double escape peaks from the above are checked for, 
        as they are for peaks found from doing an auto-search of peaks in the spectrum
      </li>
      <li>Sum peaks from peaks found from an auto-search of peaks in the spectrum, are also checked 
        for (although these sum-peak options can't currently be selected for nuclide assignment of the peak)</li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>If you choose to assign the peak to a nuclide, x-ray, or reaction that any other peak in the spectrum 
      is assigned to, then the color of the peak in question will be changed to the color of the other peak.
    </p>

    <p>The implementation of this scoring method can be found in the 
      <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/b38a80b6ef14a8ea21940fb8fc2558aee8a3aaf1/src/IsotopeId.cpp#L1466">IsotopeId::populateCandidateNuclides(...)</a>
      function in the code, which itself calls out to a number of other functions to do the work.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="file-query" title="How to &quot;Datamine&quot; a pile of spectrum files">  
    If you have an archive of spectrum files on your filesystem, the &quot;File Query Tool&quot;
    can be used to look through them, and match criteria like RID nuclide results, live time, dead time,
    measurement date, detector used, etc.<br />
    A <code>CSV</code> file of the results can also be exported from this tool as well for deeper analysis
    in a spreadsheet application.
  </message>

  <message id="feature-requests" title="How to request support, new features, or report bugs">
    <p>
      Feedback, feature requests, bug reports, criticisms, and just asking how to do something in 
      <code>InterSpec</code> are all greatly appreciated!<br />
      <br />
      Please email:
      <div style="text-align: center; font-size: larger; margin-top: 5px;"><a href="mailto:InterSpec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a></div>
    </p>
    <p>Most improvements and features implemented in <code>InterSpec</code> since 2019 have
      been a result of user feedback.  A lot of times when a user has expressed not knowing
      how to do something, or expressed frustration at how hard something is to do, this has
      led to very nice improvements.  User requests also weigh heavily into deciding which
      new features to implement.  All feedback, even if not direct feedback, is given serious 
      consideration and recorded; a number of times after a few days or weeks of thought, 
      the feedback that initially may not have seemed within scope, or only applicable to a very specific use-case,
      will <em>click</em> with the primary author and a more generalized solution can be implemented
      improving the overall experience. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Contributions to <code>InterSpec</code> are also welcome and greatly appreciated, either 
      through github pull-requests, or via other means.  Pull-requests for minor bugs or fixes
      can usually be accepted pretty easily.  For larger feature additions, please 
      email <a href="mailto:InterSpec@sandia.gov">InterSpec@sandia.gov</a> first to coordinate,
      and you will also be asked to sign an authorship memo to protect our ability to freely
      distribute <code>InterSpec</code>.
    </p>
    <p><code>InterSpec</code> is primarily developed and supported with only a minority 
      fraction of the primary authors time, so not everything can be implemented, or it may take 
      a while before something can be gotten to.
      Responses to email may take a while if the author is on travel or vacation, 
      and it is possible resources will not be available to provide requested support.
    </p>
  </message>
</messages>
