<div align="center">
      <h1 id="activity-shielding-dialog">
            <b>Activity Shielding Fit</b>
      </h1>
      <hr />
	  </div>

            <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ActShieldFit.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px; "/>

      <div >
         <u>Select</u>
         <b>Tools &#8594; Activity Shielding Fit</b> to launch the tool.
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         In the leftmost box in the tool window,
         <u>check/uncheck</u>
         under the &#34;Use&#34; column the peaks you wish to use in determining the activity of the shielding; 
checked boxes indicate a "false" peak.
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         <u>Check/uncheck</u>
         the box next to &#34;Multiple nuclides contribute to peak&#34; located at the bottom left corner of the window to account for cases when two nuclides may be the cause of 
the same gamma peak.
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         When peaks from your background spectrum may interfere with your foreground spectrum,
         <u>check/uncheck</u>
         the box next to &#34;Subtract Background Peaks&#34; located at the
 bottom left corner of the window.
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         To account for more shielding, including advanced cases of shielding,
         <u>select</u>
         the
         <b>Material</b>
         icon located at the top right of the window to add a shielding source, 
and
         <u>select</u>
         the appropriate material/thickness accordingly. For a material that is not provided under the
         <b>Material</b>
         option select the
         <b>Generic</b>
         icon,
         <u>input</u>
         the 
&#34;Areal Dens.[ity]&#34; and atomic number.
      </div>
      <div>
         <ul>
            If accounting for shielding here, be sure to
            <u>check/uncheck</u>
            the &#34;Fit&#34; box located to the right of each
            <b>Material</b>
            or
            <b>Generic</b>
            box you wish to be 
incorporated in your spectrum. This ability allows you to immediately see the effects of a small variance in the shielding source such that you can better determine 
the accurate choice of shielding material.
         </ul>
      </div>
      <div>
         You can also "Import Source Shielding XML Model" by
         <u>hovering</u>
         the cursor over the
         settings
         icon (
         <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/cog.png" valign="middle"/>
         )in the top right of the window, and
         <u>selecting</u>
         &#34;Upload Model.&#34;
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         No matter what method of inputting shielding is used, be sure to
         <u>input</u>
         the distance the measurement was taken from the shielding source in the box next to &#34;Distance&#34; 
on the top right of the window; it is by default set to 100 centimeters.
      </div>
      <div>
         <ul>The application has the ability to identify and adjust the units you input after the numerical figures; you will not need to normalize the units you plan to input.</ul>
      </div>