<div align="center">
  <h1 id="activity-shielding-dialog"><b>Activity Shielding Fit</b> </h1>
<hr />
</div>
The <em>Activity/Shielding Fit</em> tool allows for potentially fitting for source
activity, age, and shielding amounts.<br />
Before using this tool you must fit all peaks within the spectrum you want to
use to perform the analysis, and associate nuclides with the peaks.  The easiest
way to associate nuclides (or more to the point, a specific gamma or x-ray energy
of the nuclide) with photopeaks is by displaying reference lines of the nuclide
before fitting peaks so that when the peak is fit for, the association with the
specific gamma or x-ray of the nuclide will usually be automatically made.  You
can also use the <em>Peak Editor</em> or <em>Peak Manager</em> to create the
associations as well.
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ActShieldFit.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px; "/>

<h2>Source Peaks</h2>
The left-most column of the tool allows you to select which peaks you would like
to include in the fit.  Peaks must be associated with a specific source gamma
or x-ray in order to use it in the fit.  Although x-ray sources can be used, it
is recomended to not use them as their predicted amplitudes are generally less
reliable than gammas.

<h2>Sources to fit for</h2>
The middle column shows all nuclides of peaks selected in the left-hand column.
In the middle column you can select if you want to fit for activity and if
possible for the nuclide, age.<br />

Situations where you you may not want to fit for activity is if you already know
the activity, and instead would like to fit for shielding thickness, either
to a higher degree of accuracy, or you only have a single peak to use in the fit.
In these cases you can edit the activity in the middle column to reflect the
known activity (and age).<br />

For nuclides where age effects the distribution in energy of their gammas, you
may be able to fit for their age if you have multiple peaks whose relative
amplitudes will vary in time.  However, <em>InterSpec</em> may allow you to try
and fit for ages in cases where you dont actually have the power to do it, either
because the peaks relative amplitudes dont actually vary enough, or they dont vary
enough for the time regime the nuclide is in (e.x., after equilibrium), or the
problem is degenerate due to fitting for shielding or actiivites.  It is up to
you to determine if it is reasonable to fit for the age of specific nulcides.
Sometimes if you try to fit for an age, but the data doesnt actually have the
power to determine it, the age uncertainty (the last column in the table) will
be large, but this may not always be the case, so please use caution. <br />

<h2>Detector Response</h2>
You must specify the detector resposne function (DRF) to use.  You can select the
DRF by tapping on the &quot;<b>Detector</b>&quot; widget.

<h2>Distance</h2>
You must also specify the distance from the center of the source, to the face
of the detector.  You can enter the distance using entries like
&quot;3ft 4in&quot;,
&quot;3'&quot;,
&quot;13 cm&quot;,
&quot;4m 100mm&quot;, where if mutliple distances are entered they are summed
(so the last example would give 4.1m).

<h2>Shielding</h2>
You can add &quot;Material&quot; or &quot;Generic&quot; shieldings, where
&quot;Material&quot; shieldings are common materials like plywood, stainless steel, copper,
plexiglass, etc.  The material library is drawn from the NIST material database,
as well as various other sources.  With material shieldings you can either specify a
thickness, or fit for a thickness.
Generic material allows you to specify and/or fit the effective atomic number
and areal density (g/cm<sup>2</sup>) of the shielding.

<h2>Graphic</h2>
By default the chart shown by this tools is something like a &chi; chart where
it visualizes how many statistical standard deviations each peak is away from the
activity, age, and shieldings currently shown on the tool (e.g., the model).
That is, if the fit peak has four standard deviations more counts than the model
would predict, a red dot will be shown on the graphic at the energy of the peak,
and y-value of 4.  Only statistical uncertainties of the fit peak are taken into
account.<br />

If instead you uncheck the <b>Show Chi Graphic</b> option, the chart shows the
<em>multiple</em> of each peaks counts from what the model predicts.

<h2>Options</h2>
<ul>
<li><b>Multiple nuclides contribute to peak</b>: Currently in <em>InterSpec</em>
   a single gamma or x-ray is associated with each peak, however often times for
   spectra with multiple nuclides, or for nuclides with many gammas, more than
   one source gamma/x-ray may contribute to the observed peak.  Checking this
   option (the default) allows summing the contributions from all nuclides in the
   fit, and all gammas/x-rays of each nuclide that may contribute to the peak, so
   that these multiple contributions can be accounted for in calculating the models
   expected count for the peak.
  </li>
  <li><b>Subtract Background Peaks</b>: If your source peaks coorespond to peaks
    that may also be found in the background, then this option will effectively
    subtract the background peak amplitudes from the foreground peak amplitudes.
    To use this feature, first load the background spectrum as a foreground, and
    fit for all the relevant peaks (you do not need to associate nuclides with
    them), then load the item of interest as the foreground spectrum and identify
    peaks associated with nuclides as usual, but also use the <em>File Manager</em>
    or <em>Spectrum Files</em> tool to load the background file as background to.
    Once you do this, this option should become available.
  </li>
  <li><b>Isotopes of same element same age</b>: When fitting for the age of multiple
   isotopes, that are all of the same element (e.x., U-235 and U-238), then selecting
   this option will constrain the ages of the nuclides for the same element to all
   have the same age in the fit.
  </li>
  <li><b>Show Chi Graphic</b>: Toggles the graphic to either show the standard
   deviations the data is away from the models prediction, or to show the multiple
   of counts the prediction is away from the model.
  </li>
</ul>

<h2>Fitting the Model</h2>
Once you have selected which peaks you want to use in the fit, the activities,
ages, and shieldings you want to fit, the &quot;<b>Perform Model Fit</b>&quot;
will perform a &chi;<sup>2</sup> based fit of the model to data.<br />

The quality of the fit to data can generally be determined from the graphic.
You want the dots on the &chi; graphic to be within &plusmn;10 of zero, ideally within
&plusmn;2 or &plusmn;3 of zero.  If you are vieweing the graphic as the multiple chart,
you want each of the peaks to be near one.  You can use these charts to eliminate
outlying peaks (that may be due to being associated with the wrong uclide or
gamma/x-ray, or other interfering sources), or make tweaks to what you are fitting
for in the model.  Uncertainties are also provided for the fit quantities that
may be useful to determine if you have the power to fit for a given quantity;
however, sometimes this may not always be a relieable way to deterine this.


<h2>Further Options</h2>
The gear icon in the upper right hand corner of the tool provides access to a
detailed calculation log that show exactly what went into calculating the final
answer.  This menu also provides facilities to save/load/export/import model
files.

<h2>Limitations</h2>
<ul>
  <li>There are many ways the model may be degenerate given the input data.
    <em>InterSpec</em> will not be able to detect most of these situations, and
    you must vigilant about not fitting for degenerative quantities.<br />
    An example is that you cant fit for the areal density and atomic number of
    shielding if you only have two peaks in the spectrum.
  </li>
  <li>Uncertainties given in the fit may not be trustworthy.
  </li>
  <li>The calculation log should be consulted to ensure everything is reasonable.
  </li>
  <li>You must use at least as many peaks in the fit as quantities you want to fit.
  </li>
  <li>All answers must be sanity checked for correctness.
  </li>
</ul>
