<div align="center">
  <h1 id="activity-shielding-dialog"><b>Activity Shielding Fit</b> </h1>
<hr />
</div>
The <em>Activity/Shielding Fit</em> tool allows for potentially fitting for source
activity, age, and shielding amounts.<br />
Before using this tool you must fit all peaks within the spectrum you want to
use to perform the analysis, and associate nuclides with the peaks.  The easiest
way to associate nuclides (or more specifically, a gamma or x-ray energy
of the nuclide) with photopeaks is by displaying reference lines of the nuclide
before fitting peaks so that when the peak is fit for, the association with the
specific gamma or x-ray of the nuclide will usually be automatically made.  You
can also use the <em>Peak Editor</em> or <em>Peak Manager</em> to create the
associations as well.
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ActShieldFit.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px; "/>

<h2>Source Peaks</h2>
The left-most column of the tool allows you to select which peaks you would like
to include in the fit.  Peaks must be associated with a specific source gamma
or x-ray in order to use it in the fit.  Although x-ray sources can be used, it
is recomended to not use them as their predicted amplitudes are generally less
reliable than gammas.

<h2>Sources to fit for</h2>
The middle column shows all nuclides of peaks selected in the left-hand column.
In the middle column you can select if you want to fit for activity and if
possible for the nuclide, age.<br />

Situations where you you may not want to fit for activity is if you already know
the activity, and instead would like to fit for shielding thickness, either
to a higher degree of accuracy, or you only have a single peak to use in the fit.
In these cases you can edit the activity in the middle column to reflect the
known activity (and age).<br />

For nuclides where age effects the distribution in energy of their gammas, you
may be able to fit for their age if you have multiple peaks whose relative
amplitudes will vary in time.  However, <b>InterSpec</b> may allow you to try
and fit for ages in cases where you dont actually have the power to do it, either
because the peaks relative amplitudes dont actually vary enough, or they dont vary
enough for the time regime the nuclide is in (e.x., after equilibrium), or the
problem is degenerate due to fitting for shielding or actiivites.  It is up to
you to determine if it is reasonable to fit for the age of specific nulcides.
Sometimes if you try to fit for an age, but the data doesnt actually have the
power to determine it, the age uncertainty (the last column in the table) will
be large, but this may not always be the case, so please use caution. <br />

<h2>Detector Response</h2>
You must specify the detector resposne function (DRF) to use.  You can select the
DRF by tapping on the &quot;<b>Detector</b>&quot; widget in the upper right-hand
part of this tool.

<h2>Distance</h2>
You must also specify the distance from the center of the source, to the face
of the detector.  You can enter the distance using entries like
&quot;3ft 4in&quot;,
&quot;3'&quot;,
&quot;13 cm&quot;,
&quot;4m 100mm&quot;, where if multiple distances are entered they are summed
(so the last example would give 4.1m).

<h2>Geometry</h2>
You can select the shielding geometry to be spherical, end-on cylindrical, side-on cylindrical, or
rectangular.<br />
For point sources the geometry is largely irrelevant, since its only the material between the source
and the detector that affect attenuation, so it is recommended to use spherical geometry for
simplicity.<br />
The different geometries are most useful for self-attenuating sources, or trace-sources; both cases
where the volumetric distribution of the source radioactive material impact the relative attenuation
of detected gamma rays.

<h2>Shielding</h2>
You can add &quot;Material&quot; or &quot;Generic&quot; shieldings, where
&quot;Material&quot; shieldings are common materials like plywood, stainless steel, copper,
plexiglass, etc.  The material library is drawn from the NIST material database,
as well as various other sources.  With material shieldings you can either specify a
fixed dimension, or fit for it.
Generic material allows you to specify and/or fit the effective atomic number
and areal density (g/cm<sup>2</sup>) of the shielding; if combined with material
shieldings, the generic shielding does not take up any volume.

<h3>Volumetric Shielding Sources</h3>
<h4>Self-Attenuating Sources</h4>
When a shielding material contains the same element as one of the isotopes whose activity is being
fit for, an option will appear in the shielding display to have the shielding be a source for the
activity. That is, you will specify the fraction of that element the isotope composes, and then the
activity, and physical distribution of that source isotope will be determined by the shieldings
extent.<br />
When you select the shielding to be the source for an isotope, the option to allow fitting the
isotope activity will disappear from the center table; this is because the isotopes activity will
now be determined by the materials composition, and the fraction of the element the isotope is
assigned.<br />
When you have multiple isotopes of an element, an option to fit for their relative abundances will
also appear after you have selected two or more isotopes to be source isotopes.  An example of this
is shown below.  Note that the sum abundance of the isotopes will remain fixed during the fit.  That
is, if before fitting you assign isotope 1 to have a mass fraction of 0.1, and isotopes 2 to be 0.4,
then after fitting the mass fraction of isotope 1 and isotope 2 will still sum to 0.5, although
their individual values will likely change.
<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_self_atten.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 75%" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
An example of assigning a shielding to be a self-attenuating source for U235 and U238.  The relative
abundance of U235 and U238 will also be fit for.
</div>
</div>

<p>
Self-attenuating sources are particularly useful for higher mass-number elements like Tungsten,
Thorium, Uranium and Plutonium because these dense materials often provide a significant amount
of attenuation before the gammas leave the object, and the radioactive isotopes are distributed
over the volume of the object, making point-source approximations very poor.
</p>
<p><b>InterSpec</b> uses a ray-trace algorithm coupled to an adaptive quadrature based numerical
integration scheme to take into account the attenuation in the shieldings on the way to the
detector, from the entire shieldings volume, to calculate the expected full-energy peak areas.
</p>

<h4>Trace Sources</h4>
Trace sources are similar to self-attenuating sources in that they are treated as volumetric
sources that use a ray-trace algorithm to compute expected contributions, but they different in that
the source isotopes do not have to be of an element in the shielding, the source isotope strength is
not tied to the density or composition of the shielding, and the source isotope do not affect the
attenuation properties of the shielding.
<br />
Trace source can be determined as total activity in the shielding, activity per volume
(activity/cm<sup>3</sup>), activity per gram, or as an exponentially distributed surface
contamination.
<br />
<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/add_trace_source.png" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 40%; width: 275px;" align="middle" />
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/trace_source_example.png" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 40%; width: 275px;" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
[Left] how to add a trace source to a shielding.<br />
[Right] Example of how a shielding area looks after adding a trace source to it.
</div>
</div>
<p>You can add as many trace source isotopes to a shielding as you have in the currently selected
peaks to use in the fit.  However, you can only use each isotope in your problem in a maximum of
one shielding as either a self-attenuating source, or trace source.
</p>
<p>If you select the trace source to be of type &quot;per m^2 exp&quot;, the source term will be
exponentially distributed from the surface of the shielding.  This option is most often used for
soil contamination, using an end-on cylindrical, or a rectangular geometry.  When this option is
selected you will have to enter a &quot;Relaxation Distance&quot;, which is the distance from the
surface at which 63% of the contamination is contained within.
See the <a href="https://sandialabs.github.io/InterSpec/tutorials/" target="_blank">InterSpec
tutorials</a> further information.
</p>
<p>A current limitation in <b>InterSpec</b> is that detector response function does not have a
angular dependent component, and assumes the same efficiency no matter the angle or position of the
incoming gamma ray.  For volumetric sources that are comparable or larger than the distance to the
detector, this can result in some inaccuracies.  For surface contamination measurements with the
detector 1 meter from the ground, this may lead to inaccuracies of 10% or so, with lower energy
gammas generally being effected more.
</p>

<h2>Graphic</h2>
By default the chart shown by this tools is something like a &chi; chart where
it visualizes how many statistical standard deviations each peak is away from the
activity, age, and shieldings currently shown on the tool (e.g., the model).
That is, if the fit peak has four standard deviations more counts than the model
would predict, a red dot will be shown on the graphic at the energy of the peak,
and y-value of 4.  Only statistical uncertainties of the fit peak are taken into
account.<br />

If instead you choose to display the <b>Mult.</b>-style, the chart shows the
<em>multiple</em> of each peaks counts from what the model predicts, as well as 1-sigma
statistical error bars.


<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_chi_plot.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%;" align="middle" />
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_mult_plot.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%;" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
[Left] Example <b>&chi;</b>-style chart showing number of statistical sigmas each peak is away from the models nominal value.<br />
[Right] The same data, but presented in the <b>Mult.</b>-style chart option.  1-sigma error bars are shown for each data-point, with some errors being smaller than visible.
</div>
</div>

<p>
This chart can help to identify situations when not enough shielding is present (the data points
have a general positive trend), too much shielding is present (data points have a general negative
trend), or the effective atomic number of the shielding is to high or too low (the data points
are concave upwards or downwards after fitting).

<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_to_much_shield.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%;" align="middle" />
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_to_low_z.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%;" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
[Left] Example of too much shielding being present, indicated by the clear trend of data points at the different energies.
<br />
[Right] Example of shielding being too low of an atomic number, as shown by data points generally being concave downwards.
</div>
</div>


</p>

<h3>Automated trend interpretation</h3>
<p>
To help make the judgements described above, <b>InterSpec</b> automatically fits a smooth trend
to the &chi;-chart points and, when warranted, shows a short one-line interpretation just beneath
the chart.  This appears only after you <b>Perform Model Fit</b>; while you are editing the model
by hand (for example changing an atomic number without re-fitting) the dashed trend curve keeps
updating, but the text is hidden, because the interpretation is only meaningful once the activity
and shielding have actually been optimized.
</p>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/act_shield_trend_line.jpg" class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 70%;" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
The dashed curve is the fitted trend through the peak residuals, and the italic text below the
chart is the automated interpretation (here, a concave-downward trend indicating the modeled
effective atomic number is too low).  The <b>Mult.</b>/<b>&chi;</b> toggle at the right switches the
chart style; the trend curve is only drawn in the <b>&chi;</b> style.
</div>
</div>

<p><b>How the trend is fit.</b>
Under a correct model each residual is an independent draw from a unit-normal distribution, so a
plain (unit-weight) least-squares fit of the residuals versus log(energy) is used.  When more than
one nuclide is present a single <em>joint</em> fit is performed: a separate offset (intercept) is
allowed for each nuclide &mdash; since each nuclide&apos;s activity is fit independently, its
residuals already average to about zero &mdash; while the <em>slope</em> and <em>curvature</em> are
shared across all nuclides, because every peak sees the same shielding.  A quadratic is fit first;
if its curvature term is not statistically justified it falls back to a straight line, and if the
slope is not justified either, no trend is drawn.
</p>

<p><b>What the shape means.</b>
The <em>slope</em> reflects the amount of shielding, and the <em>curvature</em> reflects its
effective atomic number:
<ul>
  <li>rising with energy &rarr; the model has <b>too little</b> shielding; falling &rarr; <b>too much</b>;</li>
  <li>concave downward (&#8745;) &rarr; the effective atomic number is <b>too low</b>; concave upward (&#8746;) &rarr; <b>too high</b>.</li>
</ul>
Which of these is reported depends on what you let the fit vary.  If a shielding thickness or areal
density was fit, the amount is already optimal, so a residual shape is attributed to the atomic
number.  If both the atomic number and areal density of a generic shielding were fit, neither can be
blamed and any remaining trend is reported as a general inconsistency (suggesting distance, geometry,
source age, or detector response).  Self-attenuating and trace sources are not interpreted.
</p>

<p><b>Uncertainties and confidence.</b>
Only the statistical uncertainty of each fit peak is used (the same as for the chart itself).  Real
peak fits are, however, somewhat over-dispersed relative to pure counting statistics, so the
uncertainty on the fitted slope and curvature is scaled by the square root of the reduced
&chi;<sup>2</sup> of the residuals about the trend.  This keeps the significance
(<em>t</em>&nbsp;=&nbsp;coefficient&nbsp;/&nbsp;its&nbsp;uncertainty) well-scaled, and importantly it
down-weights poorly-converged fits that could otherwise masquerade as a strong
trend.  The wording of the message reflects the magnitude of <em>t</em>:
<ul>
  <li><b>possibly</b> (|t|&nbsp;&ge;&nbsp;1.5) &mdash; a soft advisory; expect a fair number of these to be statistical flukes,</li>
  <li><b>may</b> (|t|&nbsp;&ge;&nbsp;2.5), <b>probably</b> (|t|&nbsp;&ge;&nbsp;4), <b>strongly</b> (|t|&nbsp;&ge;&nbsp;6) &mdash; progressively firmer.</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p><b>Can the data even tell? (atomic-number power).</b>
Above roughly 250&nbsp;keV the attenuation of all elements has nearly the same <em>shape</em> versus
energy (differing only in overall magnitude, which the fitted areal density absorbs); the
atomic-number signal lives almost entirely in the lower-energy peaks.  So before making any
atomic-number call, <b>InterSpec</b> computes a <em>discrimination power</em>: the curvature
significance that a reference-sized atomic-number error (a factor of about 1.5 in effective Z) would
produce for your particular set of peaks and shielding.  If that power is too low &mdash; typically
because the shielding has removed the low-energy peaks, or there were no low energy peaks available &mdash; the atomic-number direction is not
asserted (and a &quot;silent&quot; result is noted in the calculation log as
&quot;cannot resolve Z&quot; rather than implying the atomic number is fine).  This is common for
heavily shielded sources, where the amount of shielding can still be judged but its composition
cannot.
</p>

<p>
Further detail about each peak, including these statistics, is available in the calculation log
(the log icon on the tool).
</p>

<h2>Options</h2>
<ul>
<li><b>Multiple nuclides contribute to peak</b>: Currently in <b>InterSpec</b>
   a single gamma or x-ray is associated with each peak, however often times for
   spectra with multiple nuclides, or for nuclides with many gammas, more than
   one source gamma/x-ray may contribute to the observed peak.  Checking this
   option (the default) allows summing the contributions from all nuclides in the
   fit, and all gammas/x-rays of each nuclide that may contribute to the peak, so
   that these multiple contributions can be accounted for in calculating the models
   expected count for the peak.
  </li>
  <li><b>Attenuate for air</b>: When checked, attenuation due to air will be included
  when computing expected peak intensities.  The standard &quot;Air&quot; material is
  used for attenuation calculation, with a length equal to the distance you entered to
  the center of the shielding, minus the outer depth of the shielding in the direction
  of the detector (e.g., the distance from detector to outside of shielding).
  <br />
  You may want to unselect this option if when you created your detector response
  function you unselected the &quot;Atten. for air&quot; option, and your measurement
  you are currently analyzing is at the same distance as your detector characterization.
  One scenario when you may choose to not include attenuation from air is if you
  are working with Marinelli beaker geometries, where you created your detector response
  function using a Marinelli beaker standard and the sample you are analyzing is the same
  geometry and distance (but also if you include air attenuation in creating the detector
  response, and in this analysis, things should cancel out anyway - but also if you made
  the response function in <b>InterSpec</b>, see the &quot;Fixed Geometry&quot; option).
  </li>
  <li><b>Subtract Background Peaks</b>: If your source peaks correspond to peaks
    that may also be found in the background, then this option will effectively
    subtract the background peak amplitudes from the foreground peak amplitudes.
    To use this feature, first load the background spectrum as a foreground, and
    fit for all the relevant peaks (you do not need to associate nuclides with
    them), then load the item of interest as the foreground spectrum and identify
    peaks associated with nuclides as usual, but also use the <em>File Manager</em>
    or <em>Spectrum Files</em> tool to load the background file as background to.
    Once you do this, this option should become available.
  </li>
  <li><b>Isotopes of same element same age</b>: When fitting for the age of multiple
   isotopes, that are all of the same element (e.x., U-235 and U-238), then selecting
   this option will constrain the ages of the nuclides for the same element to all
   have the same age in the fit.
  </li>
  <li><b>Correct for decay during meas.</b>: When selected, the contributions of each
   gamma line are averaged over the measurement dwell interval, with the decay and
   in-growth of nuclides being accounted for.  The resulting fit activities are the
   activities at the start of the measurement interval.  The method used does not account
   for dead-time effects, or summing effects.  The downside to enabling this option is
   an increase in computation time, and it is not usually necassary for life-times much
   greater than the measurement interval.
  </li>
</ul>

<h2>Fitting the Model</h2>
Once you have selected which peaks you want to use in the fit, the activities,
ages, and shieldings you want to fit, the &quot;<b>Perform Model Fit</b>&quot;
will perform a &chi;<sup>2</sup> based fit of the model to data.<br />

The quality of the fit to data can generally be determined from the graphic.
You want the dots on the &chi; graphic to be within &plusmn;10 of zero, ideally within
&plusmn;2 or &plusmn;3 of zero.  If you are viewing the graphic as the multiple chart,
you want each of the peaks to be near one.  You can use these charts to eliminate
outlying peaks (that may be due to being associated with the wrong nuclide or
gamma/x-ray, or other interfering sources), or make tweaks to what you are fitting
for in the model.  Uncertainties are also provided for the fit quantities that
may be useful to determine if you have the power to fit for a given quantity;
however, sometimes this may not always be a reliable way to deterine this.


<h2>Further Options</h2>
The menu icon in the upper right hand corner of the tool provides access to
detailed calculation logs that show exactly what went into calculating the final
answer.  You can add your own templates for data formatting to the log dialog
by creating a directory named <code>act_shield_fit_templates</code>, in the
application data directory (see "<em>About InterSpec...</em>" &rarr; "<em>Data</em>", and then user data storage directory),
and then saving the template(s) with "<code>tmplt.</code>", "<code>template.</code>", or "<code>inja.</code>" in the filename, for example "<code>my_report.tmplt.csv</code>".
Drop a file into <code>act_shield_fit_templates/</code> and it will appear automatically in the
&quot;Calculation Log&quot; template dropdown the next time you open the tool.

<p>
Templates are written in the <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/pantor/inja">Inja</a> templating
language and consume a JSON data model built from the fit results.  A complete
field reference and authoring guide is shipped at
<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/master/InterSpec_resources/static_text/ShieldSourceFitLog/README.md"><code>InterSpec_resources/static_text/ShieldSourceFitLog/README.md</code></a>
(also covers the batch peak-fit templates).  You can also start from any of the bundled
templates &mdash; e.g. <code>std_fit_log.tmplt.txt</code> or <code>act_fit.tmplt.html</code> in the same
directory &mdash; and modify them.
</p>

<p>
The README is written specifically to be pasted into a web-based AI chatbot
(ChatGPT, Claude, Gemini, etc.) along with a plain-English description of the report
you want.  The chatbot will produce a complete Inja template that you can save into
the <code>act_shield_fit_templates/</code> directory above and use immediately.  If the
chatbot has web access, you can also point it at the README's GitHub URL above.
</p>


<p>This menu also provides facilities to save/load/export/import model files; note, if you export a model file, you can drag-n-drop this XML file back on to InterSpec to automatically open the <em>Activity/Shielding Fit</em> tool, instead of having to use this menu to import the model.</p>


<h2>Limitations</h2>
<ul>
  <li>There are many ways the model may be degenerate given the input data.
    <b>InterSpec</b> will not be able to detect most of these situations, and
    you must vigilant about not fitting for degenerative quantities.<br />
    An example is that you cant fit for the areal density and atomic number of
    shielding if you only have two peaks in the spectrum.
  </li>
  <li>Uncertainties given in the fit may not be trustworthy.
  </li>
  <li>The calculation log should be consulted to ensure everything is reasonable.
  </li>
  <li>You must use at least as many peaks in the fit as quantities you want to fit.
  </li>
  <li>All answers must be sanity checked for correctness.
  </li>
</ul>
