  <div align="center">
    <h1 id="display">Fit FWHM from current spectrum</h1>
    <hr />
  </div>


<div style="padding-top: 10px; display: flex">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/FitFwhmFromCurrentSpectrumOverview.png"  class="imageBorder" style="display:block; margin-right:30px; max-height:250px;" />

  <p>
    This tool allows using the current foreground spectrum to fit a functional form for the FWHM
    response of your detector.  This can be useful if you would like to fix the FWHM of a peak
    to the predicted value at that energy, for instance for a low-statistic peak, or two peaks significantly
    overlapping.  InterSpec also uses this functional form, if available, as the starting peak FWHM
    when fitting new peaks.  And starting in InterSpec v1.0.13 (or the &quot;bleeding-edge&quot; build starting 20240208),
    the FWHM response is also require to compute detection limits.
  </p>
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 20px;">
  <p>
    You can access this tool in two ways:
    <ol>
      <li>
        <div style="display: flex; flex-wrap: nowrap;">
          <div style="width: 40%; column-gap 30px;">
            <p>
              From the &quot;<b>Detector Response Select</b>&quot; tool, use the &quot;<b>Fit FWHM...</b>&quot; button at the bottom of the dialog.
            </p>
            <p>
              The &quot;<b>Detector Response Select</b>&quot; tool can be accessed from under the &quot;<b>Tools</b>&quot; menu, or by clicking on the detector icon,
              <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/detector_widget.png" valign="middle" style="height:20px;" />,
              located various places throughout the app.
            <p>
          </div>
            <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/FitFwhmFromDrfSelect.png"
                class="imageBorder" style="display:block; margin-right:30px; max-height:225px;" />
        </div>

      </li>
      <li>
        If you right-click on a peak, and select the &quot;Use Drf FWHM&quot;, and there is not currently
        a FWHM functional form associated with the detector, you will be asked if you would like to
        fit for one:
        <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: space-evenly;">
          <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/UseFwhmFromDrf.png" 
              class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%; height: 150px;" />
          <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/FitFwhmFromDrfSelect_FitFwhm.png" 
              class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 45%; height: 150px;" />
        </div>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </p>
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px">
  This tool uses both peaks that you have fit, as well as any additional peaks that could be automatically
  identified in the foreground spectrum.
  It then de-selects peaks with outlier FWHM, from being used in the fit for FWHM.
  You can manually select which peaks to use in the fit (in the right-most column of the table),
  and see how the selected peaks compare with the other peaks in the spectrum, using the the displayed chart.
  When you change which peaks are used, the equation type you would like to use, or number of terms
  (only applicable to the <code>sqrt</code> of the power series equation), the fit functional form
  is automatically re-computed.  If you would like, you can manually modify the coefficient values
  that will be used, on the left side of the dialog.
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">
When you click the &quot;<b>Use FWHM</b>&quot; button, the functional form will be associated with your current detector efficiency.
</div>
