<div align="center">
  <h1 id="color-themes"><b>Color Themes</b></h1>
  <hr />
</div>

<p>
This tool allows you to customize colors on the spectrum and time charts, as well as provides two options (light or dark) for how to style the rest of the application.
</p>
</p>
  To customize the color themes you will need need to add a theme using the <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/plus_min.png"  style="width: 16px; height 16px"/> button
  on the lower left side of the tool; the theme currently selected in the menu above the button will be cloned, and a new entry added to the menu.
  By default your customized color themes are saved to <b>InterSpec</b>s internal database, but you can also download a <em>JSON</em> 
  representation of the current color theme by clicking on the <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/download_small.svg"  style="width: 16px; height 16px"/>
  icon; you can also upload <em>JSON</em> color themes by using the &quot;<b>Upload...</b>&quot; button at the bottom of the tool.  The <em>JSON</em>
  representation is convienient if you would like to use the same color theme on multiple devices.
</p>
<p>
When the '<em>Auto apply "Dark" from OS</em>' checkbox is checked, then whenever the operating system transitions into its "dark" color scheme, then <b>InterSpec</b> will automatically apply the default "<em>Dark</em>" color theme; when the operating system goes back to its default or "light" theme, then your selected color theme will be applied, or if you havent selected a color theme, the "Default" color theme will be used.
There is currently no way to customize the auto-applied dark theme.
</p>

<div style="width: 100%">
  <img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/color_theme_dialog_top.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:55%; margin-top: 10px; "/>

  <span style="float:right; width: 44%">
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Theme Name</strong> will be used to to represent the theme in the menu on the left.</li>
      <li><strong>Descritiption</strong> is used for your reference in the future.</li>
      <li><strong>Backdrop Theme</strong> styles all non-chart areas of the application.  Currently only a default (light) and a dark theme is available.  More options may be added in the future.</li>
      <li><strong>Chart Colors</strong> Descriptions are provided next to each color option, but generally clicking the &quot;<strong>Apply</strong>&quot; button at the 
       bottom of the window to actually see the changes within <b>InterSpec</b> is the most useful way to check each color choice.
        <ul><li>The <strong>Peaks Use Reference Line Colors</strong> check box indicates if when you are displaying reference gamma lines, if the peaks you fit that
        will be associated with the source nuclide (or x-ray, or reaction) should take on the color of the reference lines.  This can be helpful to visually represent 
        which nuclear sources are responsible for which peaks.  Peak colors can be changed later by right clicking (or for touch devices tapping and 
        holding for a few seconds) on a peak and selecting &quot;<strong>Peak Editor...</strong>&quot;.
        </li></ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </span>
</div>


<div style="width: 100%">
  <img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/color_theme_dialog_reflines.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:55%; margin-top: 10px; "/>

  <span style="float:right; width: 44%">
   <ul>
     <li><strong>Reference Line Colors</strong>: these choices dictate the colors of reference lines.  
     When displaying a new set of reference lines, the first available color from this list, not used for a peak on the current spectrum, 
     and not used in already displayed reference lines (if you are displaying more than one set), will be selected.
     </li>
     <li><strong>Specific Source Reference Lines</strong>: these choices overide the <em>Reference Line Colors</em> for specific 
     sources, even if the color has already been used for another peak with a different source.  Customizing these choices can
     be useful, if for example you will always want Co-60 to be represented by a speific color.
     </li>
   </ul>
   You can always change the color of the reference lines to overide these choices in the <strong>Reference Photopeaks</strong> tool.
  </span>
</div>



