<!-- SAND2021-1543 O -->
<div align="center">
  <h1 id="compact-file-manager">
    <b>Spectrum Files tab</b>
  </h1>
  <hr />
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Overview</h4>
This tab allows you to select which spectrum file is displayed for each role (foreground, background,
secondary), and if a file has multiple samples, which samples to sum together for display.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/spectrum_files_tab.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 85%" align="middle" />
  <div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
    An example screenshot of the <em>Spectrum Files</em> tab.  Here &quot;Unknown_1.n42&quot; is
    selected as the foreground file, with time samples 24 through 3056 being summed together for display and analysis.
    Sample 1 of &quot;Background_1.n42&quot; file is being displayed as the background, with a scale
    factor of 5.06 being applied to compensate for its live time only being about 20% that of the foreground.
    And on the right, for the secondary spectrum, the selection is being done, allowing you to see all the currently
    opened spectrum files.
  </div>
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>InterSpecs Memory Model</h4>
When you load a spectrum file into <b>InterSpec</b>, either through dragging-and-dropping the file into
<b>InterSpec</b>, or opening it through the menu, all previous spectra you have open, and all your
changes to them stay in memory.  That is, using the <em>Spectrum Files</em> tab, or the
<em>Spectrum Manager</em>, can can switch between spectrum files without losing work you've done,
like peaks being fit, activity/source models fit, or energy calibrations.
<p>
Spectrum files may contain many spectrum within them, maybe from multiple detectors, and/or from
multiple different points in times.  Each set of spectra within a file with a specific start time
are assigned a sample number when loading.  So if a spectrum file contains data from multiple
detectors, like an RPM or search system might, the spectra from each detector will typically be
synchronized in time, so the spectra from all detectors that start at the same time, will have the
same sample number.  A combination of a sample number and detector name (see the &quot;View&quot; &rarr;
&quot;Detectors&quot; menu) will uniquely specify a single spectrum in a spectrum file.
</p>
<p>
<b>InterSpec</b> associates peaks fit for a foreground with the foreground file and set of sample numbers
currently being shown.  So if you change the sample numbers being shown, your previous peaks will no
longer be visible; however, if you switch back to the original sample number(s), your previously fit peaks
will be displayed again.
</p>
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Specifying Sample Numbers</h4>
If the currently selected spectrum file contains multiple samples, you can choose which ones are
used for displaying of the spectrum.  If you select multiple time samples, they will be summed
together.
<br />
An example of selecting multiple samples is if you enter the text: &quot;<code>1-4,8,10,13-44</code>&quot;.
<br />
This selects samples 1 through 4, 8, 10, and 13 through 44 to be summed together before being displayed for analysis.
<br />
If the spectrum file is from a search system or radiation portal monitor, a chart with the time history of
gamma and neutron counts will be displayed; that chart lets you use your mouse and modification keys
(e.g., <code>shift</code>, <code>option</code>, <code>alt</code>) to interactively select the samples to
use as foreground and background; when using the time chart to select regions to use, the sample
numbers on this <em>Spectrum Files</em> tool will automatically be updated.
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Scale Factor</h4>
By default, the background and secondary spectra will be live-time normalized to the foreground when loaded.
For example, if the live-time of the background is twice as long as the foreground, a scale
factor of 0.5 will be applied to the number of counts in each channel of the background spectrum when its display.
This is usually what you want as it makes the two spectrums easily visually compared.
However, there are times when you will want to manually adjust this, like if the foreground was taken in a
different location than the background, so you need to scale the background spectrum to account
for higher or lower terrestrial radiation rates.  You can do this by manually changing the scale factor
on this <em>Spectrum Files</em> tab, or, more conveniently, you can graphically alter the scale factor by
selecting the &quot;Show Y-Axis Scalers&quot; options from the &quot;View&quot; menu, which will then display
some sliders on the spectrum chart that you can drag to do the adjustment in a more intuitive way.
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Additional Buttons</h4>
The &quot;Spectrum Manager...&quot; and &quot;&quot; buttons on this tab will bring up dialogs that
allow you to, respectively, perform more advanced spectrum file selection and manipulation, or browse
<b>InterSpec</b>s internal database for previously saved spectra.
</div>
