<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages>
  <message id='app-title'>
<div style="font-size: larger; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;">InterSpec v. ${build-version}</div>
<div style="font-size: smaller; font-weight: normal; text-align: center;">build date ${build-date}</div>
<div style="text-align: center; font-size: smaller; margin-top: 0.5em; margin-bottom: 0.7em;">${copyright}</div>
  </message>
  <message id='copyright'>
Copyright 2018 National Technology &amp; Engineering Solutions of Sandia, LLC (NTESS).
Under the terms of Contract DE-NA0003525 with NTESS, the U.S. Government retains certain rights in this software.
  </message>

  <message id='dhs-disclaimer'>
<div style="margin-top: 1em; text-decoration: underline;">DISCLAIMER OF LIABILITY NOTICE:</div>
<div>The United States Government shall not be liable or responsible for any maintenance,
updating or for correction of any errors in the SOFTWARE or subsequent approved version
releases.</div>
<br />
<div>
THE INTERSPEC (SOFTWARE) AND ANY OF ITS SUBSEQUENT VERSION
RELEASES, SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &quot;AS IS&quot; WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY OF
ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED, IMPLIED, OR STATUTORY, INCLUDING, BUT
NOT LIMITED TO, ANY WARRANTY THAT THE SOFTWARE WILL CONFORM TO
SPECIFICATIONS, ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS
FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, OR FREEDOM FROM INFRINGEMENT, ANY
WARRANTY THAT THE SOFTWARE WILL BE ERROR FREE, OR ANY WARRANTY
THAT THE DOCUMENTATION, IF PROVIDED, WILL CONFORM TO THE
SOFTWARE. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT OR ITS
CONTRACTORS OR SUBCONTRACTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES,
INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, ARISING OUT OF, RESULTING FROM, OR IN ANY
WAY CONNECTED WITH THE SOFTWARE OR ANY OTHER PROVIDED
DOCUMENTATION, WHETHER OR NOT BASED UPON WARRANTY, CONTRACT,
TORT, OR OTHERWISE, WHETHER OR NOT INJURY WAS SUSTAINED BY
PERSONS OR PROPERTY OR OTHERWISE, AND WHETHER OR NOT LOSS WAS
SUSTAINED FROM, OR AROSE OUT OF THE RESULT OF, OR USE OF, THE
SOFTWARE OR ANY PROVIDED DOCUMENTATION. THE UNITED STATES
GOVERNMENT DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES AND LIABILITIES REGARDING
THIRD PARTY SOFTWARE, IF PRESENT IN THE SOFTWARE, AND DISTRIBUTES
IT &quot;AS IS.&quot;
</div>
  </message>

  <message id='dhs-acknowledgement'>
This InterSpec Software was developed with funds from the Science and Technology Directorate of the Department of Homeland Security.
  </message>

  <message id='credits'>
<div style="text-align: center; width: 100%; margin-top: 0.5em;">
<div style="margin: 0 auto; display: inline-block;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/DHSLogo129.jpg" alt="DHS Logo" height="67" width="67" />
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/InterSpec128.png" alt="InterSpec Logo" height="67" width="67" />
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/snl_logo.gif" alt="Sandia National Laboratories Logo" height="67" width="150" />
</div>
</div>
<div style="margin-top: 0.5em;">
  <b>InterSpec</b> is a product of Sandia
  National Laboratories (SNL) Technical ReachBack (TRB) team, funded by the
  Science and Technology Directorate of the Department of Homeland Security.
  Feedback, bug reports, testing, and suggestions for improvement have been
  provided by many members of the TRB team, as well as the wider gamma
  spectroscopy community.  The primary developers of
  <b>InterSpec</b>
  are:
  <i>Ethan Chan</i>, <i>William Johnson</i>, and <i>Christian Morte</i>, with
  extensive additional support provided by <i>Noel Nachtigal</i> and
  <i>Edward Walsh</i>.
</div>
<br />
<div>
  <b>InterSpec</b> uses a number of open-source libraries and publicly available
  resources, including:
  <ul style="list-style-type: none; margin-left: 1em; margin-top: 0;padding: 0;">
    <li><b><a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt" target="_blank">Wt</a></b> a C++ library for web development.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>InterSpec</b> uses <b>Wt</b> extensively to render the HTML based GUI, to
        facilitate user interactions, and for database object-relational mapping.
        <b>Wt</b> is available under either the
        <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html" target="_blank">GNU GPL Version 2 license</a>,
        or a
        <a href="https://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/license/Wt%20License%20Agreement.pdf" target="_blank">commercial license</a>;
        commercial licenses were purchased for the SNL developers of <b>InterSpec</b>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="http://www.boost.org/" target="_blank">Boost</a></b> C++ libraries.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>InterSpec</b> uses <b>Boost</b> for a host of tasks, including: as a dependancy to <b>Wt</b>,
        unit testing, mathematical constants and distributions, input parsing, working with date/times,
        linear algebra, hashing, supplements to the c++ language, and more.
        <b>Boost</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt" target="_blank">Boost Software License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="http://rapidxml.sourceforge.net/" target="_blank">RapidXml</a></b> C++ XML Parser.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        A slightly modified version of this library, which allows parsing of some non-compliant XML files,
        is used for all XML parsing tasks within <b>InterSpec</b>; all modifications are included and marked with the source code of <b>InterSpec</b>.
        <b>RapidXml</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt" target="_blank">Boost Software License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://pugixml.org/" target="_blank">pugixml</a></b> Light-weight, simple and fast XML parser for C++ with XPath support.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>pugixml</b> is used by the <em>spectrum file query tool</em> to parse an XPath query event XML files.
        <b>pugixml</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT License</a>. (Windows, Linux, macOS builds only)
      </div>
    </li>


    <li><b><a href="https://github.com/root-project/root/tree/master/math/minuit2" target="_blank">Minuit2</a>:</b> Minimization Package.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>Minuit2</b> is part <a href="https://root.cern/" target="_blank">Cern&apos;s ROOT</a> package, and is used to perform numerical optizations for peak, energy calibration, and shielding/source-activity fitting.
        <b>Minuit2</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.txt" target="_blank">LGPL v2.1 License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="http://www.feynarts.de/cuba/" target="_blank">Cuba</a> 3.0:</b> a library for multidimensional numerical integration
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>Cuba</b> is used to perform the numericall integration for self-attenuation sources in the shielding/source tool.
        <b>Cuba</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-3.0.en.html" target="_blank">LGPL v3 License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://github.com/beltoforion/muparserx/" target="_blank">muparserx</a> 4.0.7:</b> c++ Math Parser Library.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>muparserx</b> is used to evaluate user entered detector efficiencies, and to help evaluate expressions for the <em>TerminalWidget</em> (not all builds of <b>InterSpec</b> contain this tool).
        <b>muparserx</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/BSD-3-Clause" target="_blank">BSD License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://electronjs.org/" target="_blank">Electron</a>:</b> Package based on the Chromium web browser to build cross platform desktop apps with JavaScript, HTML, and CSS.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>Electron</b> is used to display app contents on standalone Windows and Linux versions of <b>InterSpec</b>.
        <b>Electron</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT License</a>,
        but libraries it uses may be licensed under other terms; see <b>Electron</b>s
        <a href="https://github.com/electron/electron" target="_blank">git repository</a>
        for more information.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://www.sqlite.org/index.html" target="_blank">SQLite</a>:</b> SQL database engine.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>SQLite</b> is used to save user preferences and application state.
        <b>SQLite</b> is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain" target="_blank">Public Domain</a> software.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://root.cern.ch/" target="_blank">ROOT</a>:</b> A modular scientific software framework.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>InterSpec</b> uses a small amount of code derived from <b>ROOT</b> to calculate the Landau cumulative distribution function,
        as well some code derived from the <b>ROOT</b> <em>TSpectrum</em> class to estimate the continuum for a spectrum (a depreciated feature);
        code used is marked and attributed within the <b>InterSpec</b> source code.
        <b>ROOT</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.txt" target="_blank">LGPL v2.1 License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://jquery.org/" target="_blank">jQuery</a> 1.11.1:</b> javascript library.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>jQuery</b> is used to help deal with cross-browser idiosyncrasies in the client-side java script.
        <b>jQuery</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>
    <li><b><a href="http://qtip2.com/" target="_blank">qTip2</a> 2.2.0:</b> javascript library that provides tooltip and notification tools.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>qTip2</b> is used to help make the content-rich tooltips, as well as the notifications within <b>InterSpec</b>.
        <b>qTip2</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://d3js.org/" target="_blank">d3.js</a>:</b> a JavaScript charting library.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>d3.js</b> powers rendering and interactions of the spectrum chart, gross-count time chart, and decay tool.
        <b>d3.js</b> is licensed under the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/BSD-3-Clause" target="_blank">BSD License</a>.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://querybuilder.js.org/" target="_blank">jQuery QueryBuilder</a>:</b> jQuery plugin for user friendly query/filter creator.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
       <b>QueryBuilder</b> is used to construct spectrum file queries.
       <b>QueryBuilder</b> is <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT licensed</a> javascript library.
       (Windows, Linux, macOS builds only)
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://bgrins.github.io/spectrum/" target="_blank">spectrum.js</a>:</b> The No Hassle jQuery Colorpicker.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
      <b>spectrum.js</b> is select colors throughout InterSpec when a native <code>HTML5</code> is not used.
      <b>spectrum.js</b> is <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT licensed</a> javascript library.
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://momentjs.com/" target="_blank">Moment.js</a>:</b> Parse, validate, manipulate, and display dates and times in JavaScript.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>Moment.js</b> is used to validate date/time input for the <em>spectrum file query tool</em>.
        <b>Moment.js</b> is <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT licensed</a> javascript library.
        (Windows, Linux, macOS builds only)
      </div>
    </li>

    <li><b><a href="https://github.com/que-etc/resize-observer-polyfill" target="_blank">resize-observer-polyfill</a>:</b> A polyfill for the Resize Observer API.
      <div style="margin-left: 1em; font-size: small;">
        <b>resize-observer-polyfill</b> is used to support the JavaScript <code>ResizeObserver</code> functionality for older browsers that do not natively support API.
        <b>resize-observer-polyfill</b> is <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" target="_blank">MIT licensed</a> javascript library.
      </div>
    </li>


    <li>In addition to the many libraries used within <b>InterSpec</b>, many open-source, or publicly available tools
        and resources are used to develop <b>InterSpec</b> including, but not limited to:
        <ul style="list-style-type: none; margin-left: 1em; padding: 0; font-size: small;">
           <li><a href="https://www.nndc.bnl.gov/ensdf/" target="_blank">Evaluated Nuclear Structure Data File (ENSDF)</a>: used to derive nuclear decay information and gamma cross sections.</li>
           <li><a href="http://geant4.web.cern.ch/" target="_blank">Geant4</a>: Used to extract gamma cross section data from ENSDF to a custom format for InterSpec.  Also used to validate physics calculations.</li>
           <li>A number of build tools, including: <a href="https://cmake.org/" target="_blank">CMake</a>,
               <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/" target="_blank">GCC</a>,
               <a href="https://clang.llvm.org/" target="_blank">Clang/LLVM</a>,
               <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/" target="_blank">Microsoft Visual Studio</a>,
               <a href="https://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>,
               <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/" target="_blank">Ruby</a>,
               <a href="https://subversion.apache.org/" target="_blank">SVN</a>, and many more have been used to develop, compile, link, or otherwise produce <b>InterSpec</b>.
           </li>
           <li><a href="http://prod.sandia.gov/techlib/access-control.cgi/2014/1420625.pdf" target="_blank">GadrasDRF</a>: used to obtain detector response functions and create simulated data to test against.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>

  </ul>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id='contact'>
<div style="margin-top: 1em;">
  Please email bug reports and feature requests
  <a href="mailto:interspec@sandia.gov" target="_blank">interspec@sandia.gov</a>.
  <br />
  <br />
  Due to funding and personnel availability, support may not be available.
</div>
  </message>
</messages>
