    <div align="center">
      <h1 id="detector-edit-dialog">
            <b>Detector Select</b>
      </h1>
      <hr />
	  </div>

            <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/DetEditSelect.png"  class="imageBorder" style="float:left;display:block;margin-right:30px; max-height:300px;" />

      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
        InterSpec may attempt to automatically guess the detector response function for newly
        loaded spectra if you have set the appropriate directories (described below) and a detector
        response function (DRF) with either a name matching the model of detector is found, or a generic
        detector with a similar efficiency to manufacturer published specifications is found.

         If an appropriate DRF is not found, or an incorrect one is guessed, you can change the detector via menu
         <b>Tools &#8594; Detector Select</b>, or by clicking on the detector widget (
         <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/detector_widget.png" valign="middle" style="max-height:30px;" />
         ) found in the following locations:
      <ul>
            <li>
                <b>Tools &#8594; Activity/ Shielding Fit</b> menu
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>Tools &#8594; Gamma XS Calc</b> menu
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>Tools &#8594; Reference Photopeaks </b> menu (if tool tabs hidden) or 3rd tab <b> Reference Photopeaks </b> (if tool tabs shown)
            </li>
      </ul>
      Changing the DRF in any of the above locations is equivalent.
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         The primary component of the detector response function is the
         <span title="The fraction of gammas incident upon the front face of the detector, that will be recorded within the full energy peak at that energy">
            <em>intrinsic efficiency</em>
         </span>
         of the detector as a function of energy; the detector response can also
optionally contain the Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) for peaks as a function
of energy. Some of the peak fitting routines loosely consult the FWHM of the
detector response, if its available, for the initial value of peak width when
fitting a new peak; the fit for the peak is in no way constrained by the FWHM
of the detector response. If the detector response does not contain FWHM
information, initial values of the peak width for the fit are derived from the
data, and are almost always sufficiently close to the true width to allow the
fit to converge.
      </div>
	  <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         The
         <b>Detector Select</b>
         will provide some generic detector response functions (DRFs) as well as
         an oppritunity to use DRFs from <code>GADRAS</code>, <code>SimpleMass</code>, free from equations,
         standard equation coefficients, or absolute efficiencies specified using a comma seperated value
         (CSV) or tab seperated value (TSV) file.
         The DRFs are used when fitting for shieldings and source activity, and
         displaying refernce photopeak amplitudes..
      </div>
      <div style="padding-top: 10px">
         User defined detectors (either via upload or manual equation entry) can currently only
         contain efficiency information.
		  </div>


      <div>
         <h3>Selecting Response Functions</h3>
         Once a detector is selected from the below described source options, the 
         various indicators such as the reference gamma lines should reflect the change
         efficiencies.  However, if the detector select dialog is closed, or the
         <b>Cancel</b> button <u>clicked</u>, <i>InterSpec</i> will revert back to using your previously selected
         detector.  You must <u>click</u> the <b>Accept</b> button to continue using your
         newly selected detector.
         <ul>
            <li style="padding-top:10px;">
               <b>GADRAS:</b>
               <div>
                 InterSpec can use the same format DRF as used by
                 <a target="_blank" href="https://rsicc.ornl.gov/codes/psr/psr6/psr-610.html">GADRAS-DRF</a>
                 as long <code>GADRAS-DRF</code> has previously used with the DRF in order to create the <code>Efficiency.csv</code> file
                 to go along with <code>Detector.dat</code>.  Using <code>GADRAS-DRF</code> detector response functions has the advantage
                 of including both intrinsic efficiency and FWHM information (which may help peak fitting).  For further information
                 on <code>GADRAS-DRF</code> detector response functions see:
                 <a target="_blank" href="http://prod.sandia.gov/techlib/access-control.cgi/2014/1420625.pdf">GADRAS-DRF 18.5 User’s Manual</a>.
                 In order to use GADRAS-DRF response functions you must point the <em>GADRAS</em> tab of the <em>Detector Select</em>
                 to the root directory of your GADRAS-DRF detectors.  This root directory will be saved as a user preference across
                 sessions.

                 The discrete energy/efficiency pairs in the <code>Efficiency.csv</code> file are interpolated between using
                 Akima interpolation. The <code>Detector.dat</code> file that defines the detector in
                 <code>GADRAS-DRF</code>, is used to determine the FWHM information.
                 Specifically parameter 6, 7, and 8 (denoted by P6, P7, and P8 respectively)
                 are used according the following pseudo-code:
                 <pre>
def getFWHM( energy ):
    //P6---&gt; resolution @ E=0 (keV)
    //P7---&gt; % FWHM @ 661 keV
    //P8---&gt; resolution power
    if energy ≥ 661 or P6=0
        return 6.61×P7×(energy/661)<sup>P8</sup>
    if P6 &lt; 0.0
        var p = P8<sup>1.0/log(1.0-P6)</sup>
        return 6.61×P7×(energy/661)<sup>p</sup>
  
    if P6 &gt; 6.61×P7
        return P6;
  
    var p = sqrt((6.61×P7)<sup>2</sup>-P6<sup>2</sup>)/6.61;
    return sqrt(P6<sup>2</sup>+(6.61×p×(energy/661)<sup>P8</sup>)<sup>2</sup>)
                 </pre>
               </div>
            </li>
            <li style="padding-top:10px;">
               <b>Rel. Eff:</b>
               <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                 The &#34;Rel. Eff.&#34; detector response functions are specified using
                 CSV or TSV files that provide detector dimensions and relative efficiencies at a given distance.
                 A single CSV or TSV file may contain multiple lines with each line specifying a DRF.
                 The format of the file is:
                 <ul>
                   <li>Lines starting with the string "#credit:" will be displayed to the user to provide context/credit/information about the DRFs contained in the file.  XHTML may be used in the descriptions. Lines otherwise starting with a "#" character will be ignored.
                   </li>
                   <li>The relative efficiency is specified using an equation of the form:
                     <div><code>exp( c0 + c1*x<sup>1</sup> + c2*x<sup>2</sup> + c3*x<sup>3</sup> + c4*x<sup>4</sup> + c5*x<sup>5</sup> + c6*x<sup>6</sup> + c7*x<sup>7</sup>)
                     </code></div>
                     Where <code>x</code> is the energy in MeV, and <code>c0</code>, <code>c1</code>, etc are specified in the CSV or TSV file.
                   </li>
                   <li>Multiple files containing DRFs may be specified, and will remembered across user sessions.</li>
                   <li>The columns in the CSV/TSV are:
<div style="width: 100%; overflow-x: auto">
<table style="border: 1px solid black;">
<tr><th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">1: Display Name</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">2: Eff rel. to 3x3 NaI</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">3: Name</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">4: c0</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">5: c1</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">6: c2</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">7: c3</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">8: c4</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">9: c5</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">10: c6</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">11: c7</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">12: p0 (unused)</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">13: p1 (unused)</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">14: p2 (unused)</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">15: Calib Distance (cm)</th>
<th style="white-space: nowrap;border: 1px solid black;padding: 2px;">16: Radius (cm)</th>
</tr></table>
</div>
                   </li>
                   </ul>
               </div>
            </li>
            <li style="padding-top:10px;">
               <b>Upload:</b>
               <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                  You can upload a a CSV file that lists the intrinsic efficiency at multiple
energies in order to create a detector response function in
                  <i>InterSpec</i>
                  .
The first column of the CSV file should be the energy in keV, and the second
column should be the percent efficiency (a decimal number between 0 and 100) for
a gamma at that energy striking the detector face to be detected within the
photopeak centered at that energy.  Subsequent columns on each line are ignored.
Lines in the file characterized by first non-whitespace character other
than a digit are skipped.  The file may also be delimited by commas, spaces or
tabs; multiple contiguous delimiters are treated as a single delimiter.
                  <div style="padding-top:10px;">An acceptable input file may look like:</div>
                  <div style="color: green; border: 1px solid black; padding: 2px; width:14em; margin-bottom:10px;margin-left:10px;">
                     <div>Energy (keV), Efficiency (%)</div>
                     <div>10, 0.0</div>
                     <div>20,10.3</div>
                     <div>25 28.3</div>
                     <div>30,43.6</div>
                     <div>35  54.0</div>
                     <div>...</div>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     The
                     <b>Efficiency.csv</b>
                     file produced by &#34;GADRAS&#34; inside a detector files
folder is an acceptable input.
                  </div>
                  <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                     After uploading the efficiency file, you will be prompted to either enter the
detector diameter, or upload a
                     <em>Detector.dat</em>
                     file from &#34;GADRAS&#34; so that
the geometrical efficiency can be calculated.  If a
                     <em>Detector.dat</em>
                     is uploaded, the detectors peak width response will also be known to
                     <i>InterSpec</i>
                     as well.
                     <ul> <div style="padding-top:10px;">The detectors' name will automatically be assigned to be the same as the 
efficiency CSV file (minus the extension) used to create the detector.</div> </ul>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                  When evaluating efficiencies for energies between the provided values, Akima
Interpolation is used.  This interpolation method was chosen as it is continually
differentiable, only uses data from next neighbor points to determine value,
and does not suffer from the same overshoots or oscillations that polynomial
splines (e.g. third order splines) suffer from.
                  <div align="center">
                     <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/akima_interpolation.png"   class="imageBorder" style="margin-left:10px" />
                     <div>
					 A comparison of Akima, Cubic Spline, and linear interpolation methods for a set 
of intrinsic efficiency pairs provided by &#34;GADRAS&#34; for a hand-held detector.
					</div>
                     <div>
                        <b>Note: we have to improve this chart!</b>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </li>
            <li style="padding-top:10px;">
               <b>Formula:</b>
               <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                  If either the
                  <i>intrinsic</i>
                  or
                  <i>absolute</i>
                  efficiency is known
as a mathematical function of energy (represented by &#34;&#215;&#34; in the input function), 
it may be entered here; the detector diameter must also be known.  The formula 
entered may use energy in either keV or MeV as long as the appropriate check box 
is selected.  The evaluated formula should yield a number between 0 and 1 for 
the energy range it is valid in. The input formula must be a function of a 
single variable (energy) represented as a
                  &#34;&#215;&#34;
                  in the formula.
				  <ul>
                  <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                     <i>Intrinsic</i>
                     efficiency formulas represent the fraction of gammas
which strike the detector face, that will end up in the full energy photopeak
of the gammas incident energy.
                  </div>
                  <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                     <i>Absolute</i>
                     efficiency formulas represent the fraction of gammas 
that leave the source, which will be recorded in their full energy photopeak,
at a specified distance; hence when this efficiency is selected you will also
have to enter a distance the input formula corresponds to.
                  </div>
				  </ul>
                  <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                     <u>Valid Equations:</u>
                     Equations that can be entered follow standard mathematical rules, and can make 
use of the following functions:
                     <div style="margin-left:10px; border:1px solid black;color:blue;padding-left:4px;padding-right:4px;">
                        abs, sqrt, sin, cos, tan, asin, acos, atan, atan2,
   sinh, cosh, tanh, exp, log, ln
                        <span style="color:grey;">(synonym for log)</span>
                        , log10
                        <div>
                           <span style="color:grey;">and functions that take two arguments</span>
                           : min, max, pow
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div style="margin-top:10px;">The following arithmetic operators may be used:</div>
                     <span style="margin-left:10px; border:1px solid black;color:blue;padding-left:4px;padding-right:4px;">+, - , /, *, ^, **</span>
                     <div style="margin-top:10px;">The following logical operators may be used:</div>
                     <span style="margin-left:10px; border:1px solid black;color:blue;padding-left:4px;padding-right:4px;">==, !=, &gt;, &gt;=, &lt;, &lt;=, &amp;&amp;, ||</span>
                     <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                        Logical operations result in a  value of 0.0 if false, and 1.0 if true, and may 
be chained together, ex.
                        <div style="color:grey;margin-left:10px;">0.5*(x&lt;50||x&gt;100) + 0.75*(x&gt;=50&amp;&amp;x&lt;=100)</div>
                        will result in a function with value of 0.75 between 50 and 100, and 0.5 
everywhere else.
                     </div>
                     <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                        An example input formula could be:
                        <div style="color:grey;margin-left:10px;">exp(-343.63 + 269.10*log(x) -83.80*ln(x)^2 + 13.00*pow(log(x),3) -1.01*log(x)^4)</div>
                     </div>
                     <div style="margin-top:10px;">
                        After a formula is entered you may <u>click</u> the <b>Set</b> button to display the
function on the chart to ensure the function is reasonable; the y-axis
of this chart will always be set to display form 0 to 1.
Any syntax errors encountered during parsing of the formula will be reported in 
the
                        <b>Information and Warnings</b>
                        widget, with some diagnostics.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </li>
            <li style="padding-top:10px;">
               <b>Recent:</b>
               <div style="padding-top:10px;">
                  This is a list of recently used detector response functions you can choose to 
use again - currently this list just lists all used detector - in the future it 
is planned to only hold detectors defined from uploaded, manually entered formula,
or created from test data (a planned feature).
                  <ul> <div style="padding-top: 10px"> It is a good idea to uniquely name your uploaded or formula defined
detector response functions for later identification.</div> </ul>
               </div>
            </li>
         </ul>
      </div>
