  <div align="center">
    <h1 id="display"><b>Display</b></h1>
    <hr />
  </div>

<div style="width: 100%">
  <div>
    The <b>Menu</b>&rarr;<b>View</b> menu lets you select:
  </div>
  <img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/view_menu_mobile.png" class="imageBorder" style="width:20%; margin-top: 10px;" />
  <span style="float:right; width: 79%">
    <ul>
      <li><b>Show/Hide Tool Tabs</b>: this lets you either have the spectrum take up 100% of the screen, or show both
        the spectrum and tools to help work with spectra.  If the tools tabs are not shown, the tools are accessible from the <b>Tools</b> menu.
      </li>
      <li><b>Chart Options</b>: Detailed below, but this sub-menu lets you configure how spectra are displayed.
      </li>
      <li><b>Peak Labels</b>: These options allow you to display labels on the spectrum for <em>peak energies</em>, <em>nuclides assigned to peaks</em>, and/or <em>custom user labels</em> (which can be set using the <em>Peak Editor</em>).
      </li>
      <li><b>Show Energy Slider</b>:  Selecting this option will show a smaller version of the spectrum that allows positioning or resizing a box to define what energy range is shown on the primary spectrum.  <b>InterSpec</b> remembers if you want this chart shown or not.
      </li>
      <li><b>Show Y-Axis Scalers</b>: Selecting this option will show some slider bars to the right of the screen to allow re-scaling the background or secondary spectrum, relative to the foreground spectrum.  This can be useful comparing spectra of sources with different intensities, or from different detectors.  The scale bars are only shown, and menu items enabled if there is a background and/or secondary spectrum. <b>InterSpec</b> remembers if you want these scalers shown or not.
      </li>
      <li><b>Background Subtract</b>: makes it so the displayed foreground and secondary spectra have the background subtracted from them.
          This can occasionally be useful for highlighting small features above background to non-specialists.
          However, it is highly recomended to not generally use background subtraction as it strictly reduces information available to your eyes,
          and can often times introduce non-physical artifacts to the spectrum or peak continuums.
      </li>
      <li><b>Show 3D View</b>: This item is only enabled for search mode or passthrough data (e.g., files where spectra are taken at regular intervals).
        When enabled, this item will show a 3D view of your data with axis of time, energy, and counts.
      </li>
      <li><b>Detectors</b>: For detectors systems with more than one detector element, typicaly radiation portal monitors, or search systems, this sub-menu
        allows you to choose which detector elements to display.
      </li>
      <li><b>Feature Markers</b>: This sub-menu allows you to display expected features on the spectrum from <em>escape peaks</em>,
        <em>Compton backscatter</em>, <em>Compton Edge</em>, or <em>sum peak</em>.  When you enable one or more of these options
        if you tap on the spectrum, the energies where you would expect the effects will be shown on the spectrum.
        These options can be useful to
      </li>
    </ul>
  </span>
</div>

<div style="width: 100%; clear: both;">
  <div style="margin-top: 20px;">
    The <b>Menu</b>&rarr;<b>View</b>&rarr;<b>Chart Options</b> menu provides:
  </div>
  <img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/display_options_menu_mobile.png" class="imageBorder" style="width:20%; margin-top: 10px;" />
  <span style="float:right; width: 79%">
    <ul>
      <li><b>Log/Linear</b>: makes the y-axis (i.e., the counts-axis) either log or linear scale.  Default is log-scale as it is generally most useful.
      </li>
      <li><b>Vertical</b> and <b>Horizontal Lines</b>: light-colored rectilinear lines drawn on the spectrum to help judge energies of spectrum features.
      </li>
      <li><b>Compact X-axis</b>: Selecting this option repositions the &quot;Energy (keV)&quot; label on the spectrum to take up less vertical space.  Useful for smaller screens.
      </li>

      <li><b>Show Spectrum Legend</b> This option is only visible if you have closed the legend in the spectrum.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </span>
</div>

