<div align="center">
  <h1 id="dose-dialog"><b>Dose Calculator</b></h1>
  <hr />
</div>
<b><em>This tool has not been tested to a level appropriate for use to make any health or safety decisions.</em></b>  
Further, only basic runtime sanity checks are performed by the code to check for obvious issues; there are no unit test, 
integration tests, or end-to-end tests set up for this tool, so errors or regressions in development or implementation 
could easily happen.
</p>

<p>
Dose values computed using ANSI/ANS-6.1.1-1991 most
conservative case: Anterior-Posterior orientation.
Dose calculations are a rough guide, at best, and are
subject to many uncertainities or errors.  
When shielding is selected, an apporximate full-spectrum gamma transport methodology 
is used to account for down-scatter.
</p>


<div style="width: 100%">
  <img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/dose_tool_overview.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:30%; margin-top: 10px; "/>

  <span style="float:right; width: 69%">
    <p>This tool allows you to calculate expected gamma doses from radioactive nuclides, including effects of shielding or nulcide age.  
       Alternatively this tool can help you calculate source activity, or shielding, or distance from a measured dose.  From the menu on the 
       left of the window, select the quantity you would like to calculate, and then enter the information under the &quot;Inputs&quot; column. 
       When computing expected dose, <em>make sure you enter the appropriate distance and shielding</em>, as incorrect values will lead
       to the wrong dose values.
    </p>
    <p>Under the &quot;Answer&quot; column, the <em>Stay Time</em> table provides approximate equivalencies of dose to give a rough 
    idea of equivalent dose from commonly encountered or quoted sources.  The comparisons are only approximate, and should not be
    relied on to make health or safety decisions on.
    </p>
    <p> Note that for distances greater than 3 meters, attenuation in the air (density 1.29 mg/cm<sup>3</sup>, effective atomic number 7.37) is also accounted for.
    </p>
  </span>
</div>
