
<div align="center">
<h1 id="energy-calibration">
<b>Energy Calibration</b>
</h1>
<hr />
</div>
To perform an energy calibration, first fit for peaks in the spectrum, associating
them with the correct nuclide and source gamma/x-ray as you go along - this is
most easily done by displaying <em>reference gamma lines</em> for nuclides responsible for
the peaks.  However, if initial energy calibration is considerably off, you may have to
manually specify the true source gamma/x-ray energy of the peak in the <em>Peak Editor</em>)
or <em>Peak Manager</em> (e.g., the <em>Photopeak</em> field in either place).
You can fit for more peaks than you will eventually use.
<br />

Once you have identified the peaks you would like to use for energy calibration,
the <em>energy calibration tool</em> lets you select which peaks you would like
to use to fit for calibration coefficients, and also which coefficients you would
like to fit for, and which spectra (foreground, background, secondary) you would
like to apply the newly found coefficients to.
<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/energy_cal_tool.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:50%;" />
</div>

Once you have selected the peaks, coefficients, and options you would like to use
to fit for, tap the &quot;<b>Fit Coeffs</b>&quot; button to make the fit.<br />
If for some reason you do not like the results, you can use the &quot;<b>Revert</b>&quot;
button to undo the change.<br />
You can also manually tweak the calibration parameters instead of fitting for them.

<h2>Deviation Pairs:</h2>
Deviation pairs allow to account for non-linearities in the aquisition hardware
that can not be accounted for by the polynomial ceofficients.
For example, if after fitting the calibration coefficients the
peaks up to and including the 1120 keV peak from <sup>214</sup>Bi is at the
correct energy, but the <sup>40</sup>K peak at 1460 keV is displayed at 1450 keV
on the spectrum, then a deviation pair with offset of 0 keV should be applied at 1120 keV, and a
second deviation with offset of 10 keV should be declared at 1460 keV.<br />
Generally, once deviation pairs have been found for a particular detector, they can
be applied to all data from that detector, with changes in gain accounted for
by first-order calibration coefficient (e.g., the gain) for effects such as temperature.

<h2>Using Multiple Files:</h2>
To use multiple spectra to fit for the calibration coefficients first load each
spectrum you will want to use into <em>InterSpec</em>, fitting peaks with their
source nuclide/gamma for each of the spectra.  Then tap the
&quot;<b>Mult. Files...</b>&quot; button within the energy calibration tool.  In
the resulting dialog, select peaks you want to use for the fit from each of the
files, and select fit.<br />
Using multiple files is especially useful for lower-resolution systems like NaI
when you have seperate spectra for calibration sources such as <sup>241</sup>Am,
<sup>137</sup>Cs, <sup>60</sup>Co, etc.

<h2>Current limitations of the eneregy calibration adjustment within InterSpec:</h2>
<em>InterSpec</em> currently reads and uses the energy calibration coefficients
within files mostly correctly, however if you adjust the energy calibration there are
some limitiations that currently apply for files with mutliple detectors, or uncommon
conditions, including:
<ul>
  <li>When multiple detectors are in a file, with different energy calibrations,
    before changing the calibrations all detectors are rebinned to a common
    binning (e.g., peaks will all stay in the same place, but bin boundaries
    adjusted resulting in potentially non-integer bin counts), and that is
    varied.<br />
    To avoid this, you can select to show only a single detector at a time in
    the <b>display</b>&rarr;<b>detectors</b> menu.
  </li>
  <li>Deviation pairs will be applied to all detectors in the file.
  </li>
  <li>Energy calibration <em>type</em> (e.g., polynomial or full energy range fraction) can not be changed within the tool.
  </li>
  <li>Energy calibrations specified by channel lower boundaries can not be altered.
  </li>
  <li>The tool only shows, or allows changing coefficients up to the third order - however
    if a file included higher order terms these are retained and used.
  </li>
</ul>
All of these shortcommings may be addressed in future versions of <em>InterSpec</em>.<br />
<br />
The only known limitation of applying energy calibrations included within spectrum
files is that deviation pairs are applied using a linear variation, where a cubic spline
should be used.

