<!-- SAND2024-05481O -->

<div align="center">
    <h1 id="external-rid"><b>External RID</b></h1>
    <hr />
</div>

<p>
  The <em>External RID</em> tool allows calling out to an external REST-based internet service,
  or local executable to perform nuclide ID on spectra.
</p>



<table align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; max-width: 80%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
  <tr>
    <td style="width: 50%">
      <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_setup-min.png" class="imageBorder"  style="max-width:95%; max-height:250px; display: block"/>
      <div style="text-align: center; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px;">The <em>External RID</em> tool with URL entered, and selecting for the external service to be called automatically every time a spectrum is loaded.</div>
  </td>
  <td>
    <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_setup_with_drf-min.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:95%; max-height:250px;"/>
    <div style="text-align: center; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px;">The <em>External RID</em> tool after &quot;Retrieve DRFs&quot; button has been clicked, and the &quot;Detective-X&quot; DRF explicitly chosen.</div>
  </td>
  </tr>
</table>





<p>
  Sandia National Laboratories provides a web-based Radioisotope ID service at 
    <a href="https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov">https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov</a>,
  that can be can be integrated for use within <code>InterSpec</code>, by entering
  &quot;<code>https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov/api/v1/info</code>&quot;
  into the <b>URL</b> field on the &quot;<em>Remote URL</em>&quot; tab, as shown above.
</p>
<p>
  This web-service is free for anyone to use, and does not require an account.
  However, using it causes information to leave your computer, so it is not enabled by
  default in <code>InterSpec</code>, and you must explicitly enter the aforementioned URL into the
  <em>External RID</em> tool; this is to be sure that it can not be accidentally enabled.
  You will also be clearly warned before using this tool and notified anytime the service is used.
  Unnecessary information will also be stripped out of the radiation data before sending it to the
  service.
</p>

<p>
  The <code>full-spectrum</code> executable that can be run locally is currently not available
  for distribution, which is what the &quot;<em>Executable</em>&quot; tab is for in the tool.
</p>

<p>
  The full list of detector models this web-service is available for can be found by visiting
  <a href="https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov">https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov</a> and uploading
  a spectrum, so you can then see the list of available detectors.  Or if you visit
  <a href="https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov/api/v1/info">https://full-spectrum.sandia.gov/api/v1/info</a>,
  some JSON will be returned that provides a list of available detectors, as well as all options
  available in the service.
</p>

<p>
  If you use this tool, and enable &quot;<em>Always call on spectrum load</em>&quot;, then whenever
  you load a new spectrum file, the external service will be called, and you will be
  notified of results by a &quot;Toast&quot; notification, or a dialog if you select the &quot;<em>Show dialog</em>&quot; option.
  The identified nuclides will also be populated onto the <em>Reference Photopeak</em> tool, where
  you can then click on the nuclides to display the photopeaks; an example of the Toast notification
  and integration into the <em>Reference Photopeak</em> tool is shown below

<table align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; max-width: 80%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
  <tr>
    <td style="width: 50%; vertical-align: middle;">
      <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_toast-min.png" class="imageBorder"  style="max-width:95%; max-height:75px; display: block"/>
      <div style="text-align: center; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; width: 60%;">
        Example notification when a spectrum is loaded, and the
        &quot;<em>Always call on spectrum load</em>&quot; option is selected.
      </div>
  </td>
  <td>
    <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_photopeak-min.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:95%; max-height:150px;"/>
    <div style="text-align: center; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; width: 60%;">The external RID results
      showing on the <em>Reference Photopeak</em> tab; the <code>Co60</code> can be clicked
      to show those lines.
    </div>
  </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>


<div align="center" style="margin-top: 40px;">
    <h3 id="external-rid"><b>Information sent from your computer</b></h3>
    <hr />
</div>
The radiation data is sent to either the web-service or local executable as an N42 file.
<br />
However, before sending, information like GPS coordinates, serial numbers, embedded images,
and similar information are removed, with the files measurement start times offset by a random duration between plus and minus 1 year.
<br />
For the web-service, information sent is kept fairly minimal, with an example request and response being:

<table align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; max-width: 80%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; margin-top: 20px;">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div style="font-weight: bold;">Request header information:</div>
      <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_request-min.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:95%; max-height:350px; display: block"/>
      <div style="font-weight: bold; margin-top: 10px;">Request body:</div>
      <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_request_data-min.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:95%; max-height:350px; display: block"/>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div style="font-weight: bold; margin-top: 25px;">Response JSON:</div>
      <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/external_rid_response-min.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:95%; max-height:350px;"/>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
  On macOS, Windows WebView2, iOS, and Android builds of <code>InterSpec</code>, the system WebView
  (which is also used to render the <code>InterSpec</code> GUI) is used to make the request and
  receive the response.  On Electron builds of <code>InterSpec</code>, the Electron WebView is used.
</p>


<p> 
  Sandia National Laboratories does not collect any telemetry, usage stats, etc. from InterSpec.
  The only two places in <code>InterSpec</code> that receives or transmits external information
  from over the network are the &quot;External RID&quot; and &quot;Map&quot; tools, which you will
  be warned before using.
</p>


<div align="center" style="margin-top: 40px;">
    <h3 id="external-rid"><b>Options for using an external executable</b></h3>
    <hr />
</div>

Although the <code>full-spectrum</code> executable is not available for distribution,
other executables or scripts could be used instead.  <code>InterSpec</code> expects
the executable to put the output to <code>stdout</code> in a <code>JSON</code> format.
The invocations of this external executable or script are described below.

<p>
  To perform a nuclide ID, <code>InterSpec</code> will create a temporary <code>N42</code>
  file with the relevant foreground spectrum, and optionally background spectrum, and then
  issue a command similar to:
<pre>
/path/to/your/exe --mode=command-line --out-format=json --drf auto /path/to/tmp/file.n42
</pre>
And if there is no background spectrum available, a &quot;<code>--synthesize-background=1</code>&quot;
argument will also be added.
<br />
If a specific detector has been selected, the &quot;<code>auto</code>&quot; in the above command will
be replaced with the detector name.
</p>
<br />
  The executable is expected to output the same <code>JSON</code> that the web-service outputs; see above for example,
  or see the
  <div>
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/sandialabs/InterSpec/blob/1dc1c1d288c840082ad2d0bf3ae21d089da54a91/src/RemoteRid.cpp#L232">FullSpecResults json_to_results( const string &quot;input )</a>
  </div>
  function for the full options that can be used.



<p>
  <code>InterSpec</code> will query the executable for available detector system names, using the following command:
<pre>
/path/to/your/exe --command-line --out-format json --drfs
</pre>
And the results are expected to be output to <code>stdout</code> in the form of a <code>JSON</code> array of strings, similar to:
<pre>
    ["auto","Detective-EX","Detective-EX100",...]
</pre>
</p>

<p>
  Please email <a href="mailto:interspec@sandia.gov?subject=External%20RID%20Question" target="_blank">interspec@sandia.gov</a> with any questions about interfacing to the external REST or executable service.
</p>
