
<!-- SAND2019-9413 O -->

<div align="center">
  <h1 id="flux-tool"><b>Flux Tool</b></h1>
</div>

<div align="left">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/flux_tool_overview.png" class="imageBorder" style="max-width:60%;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px;"/>
<p>
The <b>Flux Tool</b> converts the observed counts per second peak rates into
the flux of that energy gamma or x-ray by accounting for the detector response
and geometrical factor.  For each energy, the tool gives the number of incident
photons on the detector per second, the number of incident photons per cm&sup2;
per second, and the total number of gammas into 4&pi; steradians per second.
This information can be useful for dose calculations, record keeping, or for
export for specialized applications like density determinations.
</p>
<p>
The fluxes and total number of gammas into 4&pi; steradians is the total emitted
after any shielding.  That is, the numbers given are the uncollided gammas
after any shielding materials.
</p>
<p>Since the output of this tool is primarily intended for export for use outside
of <b>InterSpec</b>, you can either export to a <em>CSV</em> file, or copy the
table to your clipboard to paste into other applications by clicking on the
&quot;Copy&nbsp;To&nbsp;Clipboard&quot; button.  When exported as a <em>CSV</em>
file all information will always be included to full accuracy (the table displayed
in the tool has limited number of significant figures), and when copied to the
clipboard all columns shown in the tool will be copied with full accuracy.
</p>
<p>In order for the table in the GUI to have any entries, you must enter a
distance and have a detector response function (DRF) selected.  The distance can
be entered in nearly any reasonable format (ex. &quot;3.2 cm&quot;,
&quot;4ft 8in&quot;, &quot;5m&quot;, etc.), and the DRF can be selected by
clicking or tapping on the detector widget in the upper right side of the tool
to bring up the DRF selection tool.  If either the DRF is not selected, or a
valid distance is not entered, there will be a prominent message displayed.
</p>
<p>The &quot;<i>show more info</i>&quot; check box lets you toggle between
showing only the energy, CPS, flux per cm&sup2;, and flux into 4&pi;, and
showing those same columns plus nuclide, intrinsic efficiency, geometric
efficiency, and flux on detector.  This option effects what information will be
copied to the clipboard, but not what will be included in the <em>CSV</em>
export.
</p>
<p>Uncertainties given by this tool are based on the statistical uncertainty of
the peak amplitude only, and currently do not include uncertainties of the DRF
(note: only DRFs fit within <b>InterSpec</b> have uncertainties), or anything
else.
</p>
</div>


