    <div align="center">
      <h1 id="gamma-xs-dialog"><b>Gamma XS Calc</b></h1>
      <hr />
	  </div>
<div>
This tool allows you to determine the cross section for gammas of arbitrary
energy through any material in <em>InterSpec</em>'s library, or any element or
material formula you enter.  If the density of the material is known or
specified, as well as the length of traversal through the material, the fraction
of gamma rays that will make it through the material without interacting with it
is also given as the &#34;Trans. Frac.&#34;.  Further, if a detector is specified,
along with the distance from the source to the detector (note this is from the
source, and not from the shielding around it), then efficiency estimates for
detection of the gamma rays inside the full energy peak will also be given.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px;">Some things to note about each of the fields are:</div>
<div style="width: 100%">
<img align="left" src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/gamma_xs_dialog.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:20%; margin-top: 20px; "/>

<span style="float:right; width: 79%">
<ul>
<li><b>Energy</b>: Values entered must be in keV and inside the range of 10 to 10000 keV.</li>
<li><b>Material/mass-formula</b>: Here you can enter any material or element in
the <em>InterSpec</em> database (e.x. Polyethylene, Air, Fe, etc.) and you will be
assisted with a suggestion popup as you type to let you know what is in the
database.  If you choose to enter a <em>mass-formula</em> instead, you should
enter the chemical symbol (e.x. C, Ni, Fe, etc.) followed by the mass fraction
of that element in the material (so a number between 0 and 1), where the sum
of mass fractions should add up to 1.0; if they dont add up to 1.0, then a scale
will be applied internally so that the relative proportions remain the same, but
the total mass fraction will be 1.0. Examples of <em>mass-formula</em>s include
'C0.5H0.2Ni0.4', 'Fe0.5U0.5', 'Al0.25Be0.35H0.4'.</li>
<li><b>Total att. cross section</b>: This is the sum of the Compton, Photoelectric
and Pair Production cross sections; Rayleigh scattering is not included in this
number since it does not effect the gammas energy.
To get the <em>mean free path</em> of the gamma through the material in cm, you
can divide this number by the density (in units of g/cm<sup>3</sup>). To get
the probability of a gamma passing through the material without interacting with
it you can multiple this number by density and thickness of the shielding
then take the exponent of the negative of this number, e.g. <code>prob = exp(-xs &#215; density &#215; thickness)</code>,
which is what the &#34;Trans. Frac&#34; field provides.</li>
<li><b>Density</b>: this must be specified in order for the
&#34;Trans. Frac.&#34; field to be calculated for you, and must be in units of
g/cm<sup>3</sup></li>
<li><b>Length</b>: This is the <em>thickness</em> of the attenuating material,
and can be entered in any distance units <em>InterSpec</em> accepts, as long
as they are specified.</li>
<li><b>Trans. Frac.</b>: The fraction of gammas that will make it through the
attenuating material at the specified energy, density and thickness, without
interacting or down scattering in energy.  Note that this is not the total
fraction of the incomming gammas which will exit the shielding, as some gammas
will scatter to lower energies and still make it through the shielding, but not
into the detected full energy peak.</li>
<li><b>Detector</b>: This is optional and will be set to the same detector as
the spectrum you are currently working on if it has a detector associated with
it; otherwise you can click on the icon and select a detector to use for the
calculation.  If a detector is selected, you will be able to input a distance
from the source to the detector to also get the geometrical and detector
efficiency calculation as well.</li>
<li><b>Distance</b>: This field will only be visible if a detector is selected.
This is the distance from the source to the detector.  Note, this is <em>not</em>
the distance from the shielding to the detector, but from the center of the
actual source to the detector face.</li>
<li><b>Detection Efficiency</b>: This is the combination of the geometrical
efficiency (the probability of a gamma from the source hitting the face of the
detector), and the intrinsic efficincy of the detector (the probability that if
a gamma hits the detector face, it will be detected in the full energy peak).
Note that this field does not include the effects of attenuation.
</li>
</ul>
</span>
</div>
