<!-- SAND2023-01080O -->

<div align="center">
  <h1 id="leaflet-rad-map"><b>Map Tool</b></h1>
  <hr />
</div>
<div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_overview.png" class="imageBorder" style="max-width:90%; max-height:300px;"/>
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">For radiation measurements that contain GPS location(s), the
map tool will display the measurement(s) as markers on a map, as well as allow you to select geographic
areas on the map to sum into a foreground, background, or secondary spectrum.</div>
  
<h2>Features of the Map Tool</h2>
<div style="min-height:238px;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_marker.png"  class="imageBorder" style="float:left;display:block;margin-right:30px; height:238px;" />
  <p>
In addition to displaying the location measurements were taken, the map tool provides a
few accommodations to help determine the relevancy of particular measurements, which is especially
useful when the data is taken by a search system.
  </p>

  <p>
As can be seen on the left, each marker on the map can be clicked/tapped to display further information
about the gamma and/or neutron count rates, the time of measurement, and other available information.
If there are multiple measurements at the same geographical location, or the map is zoomed out far enough
to make the points indistinguishable, then the measured points will be clustered together, with the
number of clustered points indicated in text; clicking on a clustered marker will either zoom into that
location, or if the measurements are all at the same location, the markers will be expanded to allow you to
click on each individual measurement.
  </p>

  <p>
The markers are also color-coded, according to the gamma counts-per-second, with the scale shown
on the right-side of the map.  The bottom button on the left-side of the map will display a
heat-map that may help isolate hot-spots for particularly large or dense spectrum files.
  </p>
</div>

<div style="min-height:265px;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_markers.png"  class="imageBorder"  style="float:right;display:block;margin-left:30px; height:265px;"/>
  <p>
    <br />
    <br />
    <br />
    <br />
The <em>shape</em> of the markers indicate if a particular measurement location is currently
being displayed as part of the foreground, background, or secondary spectrum; the marker shape
legend is below the map, on the right side, as can be seen in the figure to the right.
  </p>
</div>

<div style="min-height:265px;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_select.png"  class="imageBorder"  style="float:left;display:block;margin-right:30px; height:265px;"/>
  <p>
    <br />
    <br />
    <br />
You can also use the tools on the left-side of the map to draw shapes around given points, and then
click on the button at the bottom of the map, to sum the measurements inside the drawn shapes
and display as the foreground, background, or secondary spectra.  You can draw rectangles or polygons
on the map, as well as use the scissor tool to cut polygons from inside of other drawn shapes; you may also
draw multiple areas on the map - all of which will be summed when creating the desired spectrum.
<br />The eraser tool will remove shapes from on the map, and there is also a tool to modify the points of
drawn shapes, or change the shapes location.
<br />You may also make text annotations on the map.  However, this text has no semantic meaning
in InterSpec, and is just for display purposes.
  </p>
</div>

<div style="min-height:214px;">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_layers.png"  class="imageBorder"  style="float:right;display:block;margin-left:30px;margin-right:30px;height:214px;"/>
  <p>
    <br />
    <br />
    <br />
On the upper-right portion of the map, there is a &quot;layers&quot; menu that allows you
to choose the style of map base-tiles most appropriate for your situation.  The default is a streets
view, but the Imagery (i.e., satellite images), topographic, or gray-scale views can sometimes be more useful.
  </p>
</div>


<h2>Maps Source Data</h2>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/leaflet_map_warning.png"  class="imageBorder"  style="float:left;display:block;margin-right:30px;height:213px;"/>
Map tile data is provided by <a href="https://arcgis.com" target="_blank">https://arcgis.com</a>,
and an attribution including source data for the maps is displayed in the lower-right of the maps,
which will be dynamically updated as the displayed location changes.
  <br />
As part of retrieving the map-tile data, the geographic locations must, of course, be included in the
requests to <a href="https://arcgis.com" target="_blank">https://arcgis.com</a> servers, as well as your IP
address, and a key that associates the request with coming from the InterSpec application.
  <br />
However, no radiation data is sent to any remote server, instead all rendering of markers and other
information is done locally on your device.
  <br />
A warning, similar to that displayed on the left, will be shown, and allow you to cancel the operation,
before making any requests for map data; you may select to not show this warning again in the future.
  <br />
InterSpec is rendered using HTML and JavaScript, including the maps tool; the JavaScript libraries
for the maps tool, as well as all other libraries for InterSpec, are provided as part of the InterSpec
distribution, and <em>not</em> retrieved using network connections.
  <br />
The <a href="https://arcgis.com" target="_blank">https://arcgis.com</a> account used for the
aforementioned access key is registered to Sandia National Laboratories, and to the best of the
InterSpec developers knowledge, only aggregate usage information is available for Sandia National Laboratories
to see, and not information on individual uses of the tool.
  <br />
But if you would like to use your own key (as of Feb 2023, free accounts are available on <a href="https://arcgis.com" target="_blank">https://arcgis.com</a>), or the built-in key becomes invalid - you can
place a file named &quot;arcgis_key.txt&quot; into the apps user data directory (see
&quot;<b>Help</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>About InterSpec...</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>Data</b>&quot; for this location),
whose contents is your key, and that will be used to request map-tiles; you will be notified
that your custom key is being used when loading the map.
  <br />
With the exception of this maps tool, InterSpec does not send or request information over the internet; please see
&quot;<b>Help</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>About InterSpec...</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>Data</b>&quot;
for full information about data management in InterSpec.
</div>

<h2>Known Issues</h2>
Currently (March 2023), Windows and Linux builds of InterSpec may not load map tiles if you are
behind a proxy; the map window will still load, and markers will be displayed, and you can use the
various tools, but the underlying map images may not load.
<br />
There are two workarounds possible:
<ul>
  <li>
    You can open an InterSpec instance in your browser
    (&quot;<b>View</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>Use in external browser</b>&quot;),
    load the spectrum file, and then use the map tool from there.
  </li>
  <li> You can specify the proxy, or proxy detection settings to use, in a file named 
  '<code>InterSpec_app_settings.json</code>' placed into the apps user data
  directory (see &quot;<b>Help</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>About InterSpec</b>&quot;&rarr;&quot;<b>Data</b>&quot; 
  for this location); there is an example file with documentation you can find 
    in the InterSpec application distribution at <code>(resources/app/)data/config/example_InterSpec_app_settings.json</code>.
    <br />You will then need close all running instances of InterSpec before the change will take place.
  </li>
</ul>
