<div align="center">
  <h1 id="make-drf"><b>Make Detector Response Function</b></h1>
  <hr />
</div>

<p>
To accurately determine source activities, shielding amounts, or nuclide ages, it
is important to know the efficiency, as a function of energy, for a gamma incident
on the detector to contribute to the full-energy photo-peak.
</p>
<p>
The <em>Make Detector Response Function</em> tool allows you to use measurements
of known sources to determine the <em>Intrinsic</em> efficiency (i.e., the
probability that if a gamma of a given energy is incident on the detector face,
that its full energy will be absorbed, and it will contribute to the photo-peak)
of a detector.  Usually the the detector response function (DRF) will only have
to be determined once for a given system, and often detectors of the same model 
can use the same response function.
</p>
<p>

<div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px" >
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_overview.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:66%;" />
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Overview of creating a DRF</h4>
<ol>
  <li>Take measurements, using the detector of interest, of sources with known
      activities, at known distances.
  </li>
  <li>Open spectrum files in <code>InterSpec</code>, and fit peaks of the test-sources,
      associating nuclides with the peaks (most easily by displaying reference
      lines of nuclide before fitting peaks).
  </li>
  <li>Open the <em>Make Detector Response</em> tool, from the <em>Tools</em> menu.
  </li>
  <li>Inside the <em>Make Detector Response</em> tool, the fit peaks of each open
      spectrum file will be shown.<br />
      Select the peaks you would like to use to determine detector efficiency.
  </li>
  <li>When peaks are selected to use, an area to enter source information will appear;
      enter source information
  </li>
  <li>Enter detector face diameter, select number of fit parameters, and the type of
      equation to fit for FWHM, and other options.
  </li>
  <li>Save the DRF into the <code>InterSpec</code>s internal database for future use,
      and/or choose to download a CSV for use on other devices, or to use in
      other programs.
  </li>
</ol>
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>DRF Basics</h4>
<code>InterSpec</code> will help you to determine the <em>Intrinsic Efficiency</em>
(i.e., probability of full-energy detection of gammas incident on the detector)
by fitting your collected data to an equation of the form:
<div style="text-align: center; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px;">
<div style="display: inline-block; border: solid 1px grey; background: white; color: black; font: bold 1em courier; padding: 3px 15px 3px 15px;">
Eff<sub>pred</sub>(x) = exp( C<sub>0</sub> + C<sub>1</sub>*log(x) + C<sub>2</sub>*log(x)<sup>2</sup> + C<sub>3</sub>*log(x)<sup>3</sup> + ... )
</div>
</div>
Where <b>x</b> is energy in keV or MeV.<br />
<br />
The number of gammas at a given energy incident on the detector is determined
by the source activity, the gamma line branching ratio, source to detector distance,
the surface area of the detectors face, and live-time of the measurement.
<div style="text-align: center; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px;">
<div style="display: inline-block; border: solid 1px grey; background: white; color: black; font: bold 1em courier; padding: 3px 15px 3px 15px; text-align: left;">
FractionSolidAngle = (1 - (Dist/sqrt(Dist<sup>2</sup>+DetRad<sup>2</sup>)))/2 <br />
Eff<sub>obs</sub>(x<sub>i</sub>) = PeakArea(x<sub>i</sub>) / (Activity * Br(x<sub>i</sub>) * LiveTime * FractionSolidAngle)
</div>
</div>
Where <b>x<sub>i</sub></b> is the energy if the i<sup>th</sup> gamma/photo-peak of the source.<br />
<br />
The coefficients of the equation is fit using &chi;<sup>2</sup> minimization, where
uncertainties for each peak are propagated from the peak fit, as well as any
uncertainty you entered for the source.<br />
<br />
Some comments on taking test-source data:
<ul>
  <li>It is important that the peaks you use from the test sources at least span
      the energy range you will use the DRF for. Extrapolation outside
      the test-source energy range will often be drastically incorrect.
  </li>
  <li>Commonly used test-sources include: Am-241 (59.5 keV), Cd-109 (88.0 keV),
      Co-57 (122.0 and 136.5 keV), Ba-133 (81.0, 276.4, 302.9, 356.0, 383.9 keV),
      Y-88 (898.0, 1836.1 keV), Cs-137 (661.7 keV), Co-60 (1173.2, 1332.5 keV),
      Na-22 (511, 1274.5 keV) and Th-228, U-232, or Th-232 (238.6, 583.2, 1620.5,
      2614.5 keV).
  </li>
  <li>If any of your test-sources have peaks that overlap with background peaks,
      or the detectors seed-source (if it has one), then a background spectrum
      is also needed.
  </li>
  <li>Photo-peaks from the test-sources should have plenty of statistics
      and be substantially above background.  For many sources and detectors
      the sources generally need to be in the 10's of micro-currie range
      at 25 cm, and for between 5 and 30 minutes dwell time.
  </li>
  <li>Dead time should not be too high, as this can cause peak-distortions
      and other effects.  Very roughly, scintillating detectors (NaI, LaBr, etc)
      should probably have less than about 20% dead-time, while HPGe should
      have less than about 50% dead-time, although acceptable levels will be
      system dependant.
  </li>
  <li>Test sources should be at least 25 cm away from the detector so that
      gammas striking the detector are about parallel.
  </li>
  <li>Sources should be lined up with the detector so that source gammas will
      be perpendicular to the detector face.  Shielding should be eliminated 
      or minimized.
  </li>
  <li>It is preferred to measure each source separately.  However, especially
      higher resolution detectors, it may be fine to measure multiple sources 
      at a time, as long as their photo-peaks will be of comparable statistics.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Fitting Peaks of Calibration Data</h4>
<p>
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_open_specs.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 25%; margin-right: 10px;" align="left" />
If your calibration data spans multiple spectrum files, you will need to load,
and fit peaks for all of the files in the same session of <code>InterSpec</code>.
That is, on the &quot;Spectrum Files&quot; tab, when you are done fitting peaks
for all of your spectra, you should be able to see each of the files available
in the drop-down, as shown on the left.  The <em>Make Detector Response</em>
tool will allow you to select peaks from all of the files from your current session.
If you want to fit peaks across multiple sessions, you can always fit the peaks
and either save the results to <code>InterSpec</code>s internal database, or export
to N42-2012 files, which will save the peaks you fit.

<br style="clear: both" />

<div align="center" style="padding-top: 10px; padding-left: 10px" >
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_peak_fit.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 50%; margin-left: 10px;" align="right" />
</div>
Since the <em>Make Detector Response</em> tool will need to know the nuclide associated
with each fit peak, it is easiest to show reference lines, like is being done in
the screenshot on the right, before fitting the peaks, so this way when you fit
the nuclide, and specific gamma will be automatically associated with the peak.
You can also make this association by right-clicking on a peak, and either choosing
a new nuclide from the list of suggested nuclides, or opening the <em>Peak Editor</em>
and entering a nuclide; the <em>Peak Manager</em> also lets you set the nuclide
and specific gamma line of a peak.
</p>
<p>
You do not need to fit background peaks for your test-source spectra.<br />
If any of your test-sources have peaks that overlap with background peaks, and
that you would like to use, you should use a background spectrum with its peaks
fit; you do not need to associate nuclides with the peaks of the background
spectrum.  The background peak rates will be subtracted from the test-source
peak rates during DRF fitting.<br />
Especially for HPGe spectra of sources with lots of gamma-lines, or the background,
the &quot;Search for Peaks&quot; button/tool in the <em>Peak Manager</em> tab
can be used to automate the peak fitting process.
</p>
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Selecting Peaks to Use, and Entering Source Information</h4>
<p>
<div style="both">
You may choose to either use, or not use, peaks that you have fit for to help
determine the DRF.  Reasons to not use a peak include: not from a source of interest,
low branching ratio, high background contributions, possible interference from other sources, poor peak fit,
or a peak may just visually deviate from the reasonable range for the efficiency curve.
For this latter case, it may be worth checking that the correct gamma-line is associated
with the peak using the <em>Peak Manager</em> or <em>Peak Editor</em>; usually
<code>InterSpec</code> correctly picks the correct gamma-line to associate with peaks,
but occasionally a correction needs to be done.
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_source_info_basic.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 33%; margin-right: 10px;" align="left" />
When you select a peak to use to help determine the DRF equation, a source
box will appear under all the peaks of that file.  Here you can enter the source
distance from the detector face, the source activity, and an activity uncertainty.
If a single spectrum has multiple sources, you must enter the distance separately
for each source.  If more than one source nuclide will contribute to a peak, <code>InterSpec</code>
will take this into account, for all sources being used for that spectrum.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; clear: both">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_source_info_age.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 33%; margin-right: 10px;" align="left" />
If you only know the source activity at a previous date, you can select the
&quot;Age?&quot; checkbox, which will allow you to enter the assay date; the entered
activity will then be decayed to the date given in the spectrum file (which you
can also change here).  If it is a source where the gamma spectrum appreciable
changes with age, you will also be given a chance to enter age at assay date.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; clear: both">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_source_info_shield.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 33%; margin-right: 10px;" align="left" />
You can also choose to enter a shielding between the test-source and detector.
This is primarily useful to account for the source container, or for self-attenuating sources.
Shielding should be avoided or minimized when making characterization measurements.
</div>


<div style="padding-top: 10px; clear: both">
If the &quot;Is Background?&quot; checkbox is selected, then all peaks of that
measurement will be assumed to be background peaks.  <code>InterSpec</code> will
automatically correct test-source peaks for background peaks if there is any
overlap; this correction will be indicated in text by the test-source peak being
corrected.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_no_nuc.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:66%;" align="right" />
If you do not want to associate a nuclide with a peak, you can still use the
peak for determining the DRF; when the peak is selected to use, a entry form
will appear to enter the branching ratio of this peak, and a generic source
will also be shown to enter the activity and distance.  This feature is useful
if you think the nuclide library has an error, or you are determining the DRF
based on a simulation with arbitrary gamma sources.
</div>
</p>
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Fitting Options:</h4>
<div align="center" style="" >
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_options.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:66%;" />
</div>
<p>
You can choose how many coefficients you want the <em>Intrinsic Efficiency</em>
equation to use, with the guiding criteria usually being how well the fit
equation matches the data, without being over-fitted.
A maximum of eight coefficients can be used.
You can also choose if you would like the coefficients fit for energy in keV, or
MeV.  Usually MeV gives coefficient values that are slightly more natural
looking, but the only time the choice really matters is if you want to use the
coefficients in another application that expects one unit or another.
</p>
<p>
The detector Full Width Half Maximum (FWHM) as a function of energy is also fit
at the same time as the <em>Intrinsic Efficiency</em>.  However, since
<code>InterSpec</code> does not really use this information, it is not
emphasized in the user interface, but the information is saved as part of the
DRF, and is also written to the CSV file available from the &quot;Save As...&quot;
dialog.
</p>
<p>
The FWHM can be fit using either the square root of a power series in energy:
<div style="display: inline-block; border: solid 1px grey; background: white; color: black; font: bold 1em courier; padding: 0px 15px 3px 15px;">
FWHM(energy) = sqrt( A<sub>0</sub> + A<sub>1</sub>*energy + A<sub>2</sub>*energy<sup>2</sup> + A<sub>3</sub>*energy<sup>3</sup> + ... )  <span style="font: normal 0.75em courier">[energy in MeV]</span>
</div>
<div style="margin-top: 5px;">
Or using the FWHM equation used by GADRAS-DRF:
</div>
<div style="display: inline-block; border: solid 1px grey; background: white; color: black; font: bold 1em courier; padding: 0px 15px 0px 15px;">
<pre>
def getFWHM( energy ):
    //P6---&gt; resolution @ E=0 (energy in keV)
    //P7---&gt; % FWHM @ 661 keV
    //P8---&gt; resolution power
    if energy ≥ 661 or P6=0
        return 6.61×P7×(energy/661)<sup>P8</sup>
    if P6 &lt; 0.0
        var p = P8<sup>1.0/log(1.0-P6)</sup>
        return 6.61×P7×(energy/661)<sup>p</sup>

    if P6 &gt; 6.61×P7
        return P6;

    var p = sqrt((6.61×P7)<sup>2</sup>-P6<sup>2</sup>)/6.61;
    return sqrt(P6<sup>2</sup>+(6.61×p×(energy/661)<sup>P8</sup>)<sup>2</sup>)
</pre>
</div>
<div>
You can also choose to show this fit and peak FWHM  data on the chart by selecting the
&quot;Show FWHM points&quot; checkbox.
</div>
</p>
</div>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Save As Dialog:</h4>
<div style="padding-top: 10px; padding-left: 10px" >
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/make_drf_save_as.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width: 30%; margin-left: 10px; margin-right: 10px;" align="left" />
When saving the DRF it gets saved into <code>InterSpec</code>s internal database,
and can be retrieved in the &quot;Previous&quot; tab of the
<em>Detector Response Select</em> tool.  The name you assign can not have
symbols commonly prohibited in filenames such as slashes, backslashes, quotes,
commas, semi-colons, and question marks.  The description field is to make any
notes about the DRF you may want to recall in the future.
<p>
Clicking on the &quot;Export data as N42-2012 file&quot; option will combine
all spectra used into a single N42 file.  This N42 file can be opened in
other programs, but if opened in <code>InterSpec</code>, all of the fit peaks,
as well as the DRF will be retained.
</p>
<p>
The &quot;Export DRF as CSV.&quot; option creates a CSV with the <em>Intrinsic
Efficiency</em> coefficients, <em>Relative Efficiency</em> (i.e., efficiency at
25 cm) coefficients, peak areas, gamma counts from isotopes, efficiencies and
FWHM at 25 keV energy intervals, &chi;<sup>2</sup> of fits, and some other information.
</p>
<p>
You can also select to have this DRF automatically loaded whenever you load data
from either this specific detector (as determined by the serial number in the
spectrum file), or this model of detector (as determined by the spectrum file).
</p>
<p>Hovering the mouse, or tapping, the
<img src="InterSpec_resources/images/help_mobile.svg" width=12 height=12 alt="help" class="MakeDrfSaveHelp" />
icon will display additional tips for each item in this dialog.
</p>
</div>

<div style="display: table-row; clear: both;">
<h4>Miscellaneous Information:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>The <em>Create Detector Response Function</em> tool can be used with any
      detector types you can fit peaks for, including CsI, NaI, LaBr3, CZT,
      and HPGe.
  </li>
  <li>The error bars shown on the data points of the <em>Intrinsic Efficiency</em>
      chart are 1-sigma uncertainties based on the statistical uncertainties
      of the peak fit, the background peak fit (if applicable), and entered
      source activity uncertainty.
  </li>
  <li>The efficiency chart defaults to showing the energy range of the spectrum
      files, but the areas above the highest energy peak used, and bellow the 
      lowest energy peak are slightly greyed out to indicate the DRF is not 
      valid in those regions.
  </li>
  <li>Background peak rates are subtracted from a test-source peak rate if the
      fit background peak is within 1.5 peak-sigmas of the fit test-source peak,
      or if the background peak is assigned a nuclide and its source line is
      within 1 keV of the test-source line.
  </li>
  <li>If a spectrum has multiple sources associated with it, then for each peak
      used, not only will the primary nuclide associated with that peak be used
      to calculate the incident photons on the detector at that energy, but if
      any of the other sources have gamma rays within 1.25 peak sigmas of the
      primary nuclides line, it will be used as well.  However, the effect of
      this is not currently displayed to the user.
  </li>
  <li>If the spectrum file contains source information such as activity or
      distance, this info may get pre-populated in the tool.  A common way
      this is indicated is if the spectrum title (or remark that starts with
      &quot;Source:&quot;) is formated similar to &quot;57Co,75uC @50cm&quot;,
      where this indicates the Co-57 was 75uC, and the source to detector
      distance is 50 cm.
  </li>
  <li>The fits to efficiency and square-root power series (FWHM) are performed
      by transforming the data and equations to a form suitable for
      least squares fitting via linear algebra techniques.  However, since the
      uncertainties are no longer approximately Gaussian distributed after the
      transformation, the answer will be biased.  Therefore <code>InterSpec</code>
      uses the least squares result as a starting point for a numerical-based
      steepest decent approach on the non-transformed data and equation to find
      the actual solution and errors presented by the tool.
  </li>
  <li>Clicking on the <img src="InterSpec_resources/images/peak_small.png" width=16 height=16 />
      icon next to each peak will show you a preview of that peak, incase you want
      to check the fit quality of that peak.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>
<div style="clear: both" />
</div>

</div>
