    <div align="center">
      <h1 id="decay-dialog">
            <b>Nuclide Decay Information</b>
      </h1>
      <hr />
	  </div>

  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/nuc_decay_info.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px"/>

      <div>
         This tool allows you to obtain information about aged nuclides, such as
activities or gamma/alpha/beta production rates, or the decay chain as well as
further information about each of the daughter nuclides.  There are two main
portions of this tool used to extract information: the <b>Activity Chart</b> tab and
<b>Decay Chain</b> tabs; usage information and hints are offered in the
similarly named subsections.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px">
For both of these tools the initially selected nuclide
information will be displayed for whatever nuclide the
         <b>Reference Photopeaks</b>
         tool is currently displaying, or if it is not
displaying any reference gamma lines for nuclides, a default nuclide.
</div>

<div>
<h3>Activity Chart</h3>
</div>
<div>The <b>Activity Chart</b> display can display the activity, or emission rate of gamma,
beta, or alpha particles as a function of time for the chosen parent and
daughter nuclides.</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px"><u>Clicking</u> on the chart will bring up a text listing of nuclide activities
and decay particle types, their energies and intensities, as well as some
additional information, all for the time clicked.</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">If the check-boxes in the legend are un-checked, then the nuclide listed next to
it will not be displayed on the decay chart; this is useful when the activities
of a number of daughter products overlap (hence hiding each other) and you wish
to verify the location of the decay curve.</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">
<u>Adjusting</u> the
<b>Time Span</b>
changes the x-axis range displayed, and can be
useful for zooming in on the initial decay period.
</div>

<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/nuc_decay_select.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;clear:both;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px; margin-top:10px;"/>

<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Changing Nuclide</h4>
The selected nuclide can be changed by <u>double-clicking</u> the icon representing
the nuclide in the upper bar listing the nuclides; in the example screen shot
below it looks like:
         <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/i135icon.png" valign="middle" />
         .
Alternatively you could remove the isotope by <u>clicking</u> the
<button type="button" class="mycloseicon Wt-btn" />
<b>symbol</b> in the
nuclides icon, and then add a new nuclide by <u>clicking</u> the <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/AddNucIcon.png" valign="middle" />
icon.  You can add multiple isotopes so you can view their
decay information together.
</div>


<div style="margin-top:15px; padding-top:5px">
 <div style="padding-top: 10px">Note: The &#34;<b>nuc. search</b>&#34;
               field will update the element and isotope selection fields with suggestions as you type. No suggestions will be
offered before you enter text, but the element and isotope fields will still be
populated if you wish to select your nuclide that way.  If you wish to get
quantitative information on the activity as a function of time, you can select
the initial activity of the nuclide.  If you wish to have a minimum age
for the decay chart to start at, you can also fill in a minimum age here.</div>
         </div>

<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/nuc_decay_chain.png"  class="imageBorder"  style="max-height:300px;clear:both;float:left;margin-right:20px; margin-top:10px;" />
<div style="display:table-row">
<h3>Decay Chain</h3>

    <div>

               Example screen shot of the <b>Nuclide Decay Information</b> tool showing the <b>Decay Chain</b> tab.  

			   <div style="padding-top: 10px">
			   Note: You can <u>click</u> on a nuclide
to obtain further information about its half life, parents, and decays.  
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">
<u>Double-click</u> on a nuclide to get information about the decay products (gamma/beta/alpha)
from that nuclide.  If you have selected multiple nuclides in the upper source
area, the decay chain can only be shown for one at a time.  <u>Clicking</u> on the icon
for a different nuclide (in the example shown above, Pu239 instead of U235)
will display the decay chain for that parent nuclide.
</div>
         </div>
	  </div>