   <div align="center">
      <h1 id="1/r2-calc-dialog"><sup>1</sup>/<sub>r<sup>2</sup></sub> Distance To Source Calculator</h1>
      <hr />
	  </div>
            <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/1r2Calc.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-height:300px;float:left;display:block;margin-right:20px"/>

      <div >
<div>
This tool allows you to use two dose measurements taken at different distances
from a source to determine the absolute distance to the source from the nearer
measurement.
This is useful when the source is behind a wall or in a large container and the
position of the source can not be determined otherwise.
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 10px">
For the &#34;Near&#34;, &#34;Far&#34;, and &#34;Background&#34; intensity values
you can use an units of dose or intensity you want (e.x. rem, millirem,
sievert/hour, gamma counts per second, etc.), but it must be the same for each
field.  Similarly, you can use any unit of distance (ex. meters, feet,
attoparsecs, etc.) for the distance between the measurements, as the answer will
be provided in these same units.
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 5px">
Entering a background intensity is optional, but for the case of low intensity
sources, it will help to provide a more accurate answer by subtracting this value
from both the near and far measurements.
</div>
<div style="padding-top: 5px">
This tool assumes the source intensity falls off as <sup>1</sup>/<sub>r<sup>2</sup></sub>
which is generally the case, however there can be circumstances where scattering
or other effects will cause this to not be true; also, over huge distances
attenuation in the air will cause this assumption to be invalid as well.
You can use the <b>Gamma XS Calc</b> tool to calculate the expected attenuations
for different energies through air to see if it is significant effect.
<!-- <b>(TODO: insert some example effects at different distances here)</b> -->
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; clear: both;">
The formula used to calculate the distance in front of the near measurement is
shown below in <i>pseudo-code</i> format, and already assumes the background has been subtracted from
<code>FarIntensity</code> and the <code>NearIntensity</code>, and a low-scatter power law of 1/r<sup>2</sup> is being used.
<pre><code><i>let</i> <span style="color:blue;">a</span> = FarIntensity - NearIntensity
<i>let</i> <span style="color:blue;">b</span> = 2&#215;FarIntensity&#215;DistanceBetween
<i>let</i> <span style="color:blue;">c</span> = FarIntensity&#215;DistanceBetween&#215;DistanceBetween
<i>let</i> <span style="color:blue;">DistanceInFrontOfNear</span> = <sup>(-<span style="color:blue;">b</span>-sqrt(<span style="color:blue;">b</span>&sup2;-4&#215;<span style="color:blue;">a</span>&#215;<span style="color:blue;">c</span>))</sup>/<sub>2<span style="color:blue;">a</span></sub>
</code></pre>
</div>

</div>
