<!-- SAND2021-1543 O -->
<div align="center">
  <h1 id="peak-manager">
    <b>Peak Manager</b>
  </h1>
  <hr />
</div>


<div style="display:table-row">
<h4>Overview</h4>
The <em>Peak Manager</em> allows quickly viewing or editing properties of the peaks fit in the spectrum.
As can be seen below, you can use this tool to change the nuclide associated with the peak, or the
specific gamma or x-ray assigned to the peak.  You can also change the other properties like mean, FWHM,
or add a custom label for the peak that will be displayed on the spectrum.
<br />
Most of these actions, and more, can also be performed using the &quot;Peak Editor&quot; that can
be accessed by right-clicking on a peak.
<br />
The <span style="color: blue"><b>CSV</b></span> export capability in the lower right hand corner is also useful
to export the fit peak information for use within other applications.
<br />
Editing the information is straight-forward for most of the columns, however, it is worth noting
that if editing the &quot;Photopeak&quot; column, you must first have assigned a nuclide, element,
or nuclear reaction, and then as you type in an energy, a suggestion popup will appear giving you
the gammas and x-rays of the relevant nuclide/element/reaction.  If you precede the energy with either
&quot;S.E.&quot; or &quot;D.E.&quot; you can choose to associate the peak with a gamma where
either one or two 511 keV peaks, resulting from pair-production inside the detector, escaped the
detection element.  A common use for this is to assign the source to the 2103 and 1592 keV in HPGe
detector, which would be assigned as &quot;S.E. 2614&quot; and &quot;D.E. 2614&quot; respectively.
</div>

<div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/peak_manager.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 85%" align="middle" />
<div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
An example screenshot of the <em>Peak Manager</em> tool illustrating editing the nuclide assigned to a given peak.
</div>
</div>

<p> As can be seen from the above screen-shot, there are also a number of other peak-related functions
that can be performed from this tool:
</p>
<table style="text-align: left; margin-left: 10px;">
  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top; white-space: nowrap;">
      Search for Peaks...
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      This performs an automated search for peaks in the spectrum.  If you have reference photo-peak
      lines showing before clicking this button, you will then be able to select having only peaks
      from that nuclide fit, as well as having the peaks auto-associated with that nuclide.  The
      feature is most useful for HPGe spectra with lots of peaks; it doesn't do a perfect job, but
      often times can get you 90% there.
      For lower-resolution (e.x., NaI or CsI), manually fitting peaks will usually do a better job
      then using this feature, so it is recommended to not use it for these detectors.

      <div style="padding-top: 10px; text-align: center;">
        <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/auto_peak_search_result.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width: 30%" align="middle" />
        <div style="clear: both; text-align: left; padding-left: 20px; padding-right: 20px;">
          An example result of the auto-peak search. From this dialog you can select which peaks you want to keep, or adjust nuclide assignments.
        </div>
      </div>
    </td>
  </tr>


  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top;">
      Clear all Peaks
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      Removes all peaks from the current spectrum.
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top;">
      Nuc. from Ref.
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      Clicking this button will allow associating already-fit peaks with the currently showing photo-peak reference lines.
      This is useful if you have fit peaks, but weren't showing reference lines, or otherwise haven't associated nuclides
      with the peaks.  It does a pretty good job of selecting the correct gammas or x-rays for peaks
      when the reference lines for a single nuclide are showing, but results can be sub-par when showing reference lines for
      multiple nuclides, each with lots of gammas.
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top;">
      Add...
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      This will create a dialog that will allow you to add a peak to the spectrum.  This is useful
      for really low statistics peaks that <b>InterSpec</b> wont otherwise fit, or to force small
      peaks overlapping much larger peaks.
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top;">
      Delete
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      Deletes the peak of the currently selected row.  In the above screenshot of the <em>Peak Manager</em>,
      the row being edited is highlighted yellow, and so its the peak that would be deleted if this
      button is clicked.
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <th style="padding-right: 10px; padding-bottom: 20px; vertical-align: text-top;">
      CSV
    </th>
    <td style="padding-bottom: 20px;">
      Clicking this element allows exporting peak information in a convenient CSV format, useful for
      analysis in other programs or spreadsheet applications.  Another use for this CSV is that if you
      later load another spectrum that has similar peaks, you can drag-and-drop the previous spectrums CSV
      onto <b>InterSpec</b>, and those same peaks will be fit for in the new spectrum.  This is useful
      if you often process spectra of similar sources.
      <br />
      There is also a &quot;Ask to Propagate Peaks&quot; option in the &quot;Help&quot; &rarr; &quot;Options&quot;
      menu, that when selected, and you open a new spectrum file from the same detector as your current
      foreground spectrum, <b>InterSpec</b> will ask if you would like to fit the peaks fit in the
      previous spectrum in the newly opened spectrum.
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

