<div align="center">
  <h1 id="id-peak"><b>Peak Fitting</b></h1>
  <hr />
</div>

<p><em>Suggestion:</em> <i>Before fitting for peaks, display the reference lines responsible for the peaks if known -
this way the peak will be associated with the appropriate nuclide at the time of fitting, rather than having to be 
manually associated later to perform activity fitting or do energy calibration.</i>
</p>

<p>
The simplest way to fit a nuclide is to double tap on the area the peak is located:
<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/touch_fit_peak.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:75%;" />
</div>
</p>
<p>If there are multiple peaks in an area, you can double tap on each peak peak, to fit additional peaks.
<div style="padding-top: 10px" align="center">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/touch_multipeak_fit.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:75%;" />
</div>
</p>

<p>If there is a region with many overlapping peaks where double-tapping doesnt work well enough, you can
hold two fingers horizantal and close together and move both of your fingers horizantally to the right, 
keeping them spaced about the same, to define a region to fit mltiple peaks in.  When you let your fingers
up, you will be prompted for how many peaks you would like to fit the region you defined.
<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/mobile_multipeak.jpg"  class="imageBorder" style="width:75%;" />
</div>
</p>



<p>In the <em>Menu</em>&rarr;<em>Tools</em>&rarr;<em>Peak Manager</em> you can automatically fit for
all the peaks in a spectrum using the <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/mobil_search_for_peaks.png" style="height:1.25em;" /> button.
It is recomended to have nuclide reference lines showing before using this automated peak search so peaks will automatically
be associated with the nuclides responsible for creating the peak.
</p>

<p>
If you want to re-fit a peak, or access the <em>Peak Editor</em>, hold your finger down on a peak for about a second, 
and menu will pop up to let you choose what you would like to do.
<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
  <img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/mobile_right_click.png"  class="imageBorder" style="width:75%;" />
</div>
</p>