<div align="center">
<h1 id="reference-gamma-lines-dialog"><b>Reference Gamma Lines</b></h1>
<hr />
</div>
<div>

<p>
  The reference gamma lines tool shows energies of gamma and x-rays emitted
  by an isotope, both in a table within the tool and also as lines on the spectrum.
</p>

<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ref_gamma_lines_widget.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:55%;" />
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ref_gamma_line_spectrum.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:30%" />
</div>

<p>
A key part of performing an anlysis with <b>InterSpec</b> is associating peaks
with specific energy gamma or x-rays from a nuclide - the easiest way to
accomplish this is to display reference lines for a nuclide <em>before</em>
fitting the peaks.  When reference lines are displayed, and a peak is fit, if
there is a reference line reasonably near the fit peak, then that peak will be
assigned that energy gamma or x-ray.  Once this is done, that peak can be used
for energy calibration, or for fitting source activity, age, or shielding.
</p>

<p>
Options for using the tool:
<ul>
  <li><b>Nuclide</b> to display: All non-stable nuclides are available for display, as well as fluorescent for elements, many nuclear reactions, and some other sources;  see &quot;<em>Sources Available To Display</em>&quot; section below for more info.</li>
  <li><b>Age</b>: For isotopes where aging will have an effect on the distribution
   of gamma and/or x-ray amplitudes, age of the nuclide can be specfied using a
   combination of time units, similar to &quot;<b>5.3y 8d 22m</b>&quot; or in half lives like
   &quot;<b>2.5 HL</b>&quot;.  Acceptable time units: <b>year</b>, <b>yr</b>,
   <b>y</b>, <b>day</b>, <b>d</b>, <b>hrs</b>, <b>hour</b>, <b>h</b>, <b>minute</b>,
   <b>min</b>, <b>m</b>, <b>second</b>, <b>s</b>, <b>ms</b>, <b>microseconds</b>,
   <b>us</b>, <b>nanoseconds</b>, <b>ns</b>, or you can specify time period by
   <b>hh:mm:ss</b>. Half life units can be specified using <b>hl</b>, <b>halflife</b>,
   <b>halflives</b>, <b>half-life</b>, <b>half-lives</b>, <b>half lives</b>, or
   <b>half life</b>.<br />
   Half life units or time periods can not be mixed with other units.<br />
   When multiple time periods are specified, they are summed,
   e.x. &quot;1y6months 3m&quot; is interpreted as 18 months and 3 minutes.
   <br />
   The initial age used when a nuclide is entered is based on a heuristic that
   generally works well, but in the case of freshly produced, or extensively aged
   nuclides may need to be adjusted.
   <br />
   Adjusting the age is not allowed for nuclides whose signatures do not significantly
   change with age.
  </li>
  <li><b>Prompt Only</b>: For nuclides that have decay chains where at some point a child
    half-life is longer than its parents, selecting this option will cause only the
    nuclides in the decay chain down to that point to be included in the reference
    lines shown, with them all being in static equilibrium.<br />
    This option is only shown for nuclides where it applies, like U-238, Th-232, etc.
  </li>
  <li><b><span style="color:red;">C</span><span style="color:green;">o</span><span style="color:blue;">l</span><span style="color:yellow;">o</span><span style="color:violet;">r</span></b>:
    You can select the color you would like the reference lines to appear on the
    spectrum - this will also cause peaks fit while showing the reference lines
    that can be attributed to the nuclide, to be that color as well.  This is useful
    to quickly identify which peaks are attributed to different nuclides.
  </li>
  <li><b>Detector Response Function</b>: If a detector response function (DRF) is selected
    then the amplitude of lines drawn on the spectrum, will be convoluted with the DRF
    so that lines your detector has a lower sensitivity to will be shown with a smaller
    amplitude.  <br />
    The DRF does not effect the <b>B.R.</b> shown in the tools table.
  </li>
  <li><b>Shielding</b>: Because shielding can drastically alter the expected
    distribution of gammas and x-rays, you can enter a shielding type and thickness
    to have the reference lines shown on the spectrum be modulated by the attenuation
    of that shielding.<br />
    Shielding does not effect the <b>B.R.</b> shown in the tools table.
  </li>
</ul>
</p>


<p>
By default, reference lines for x-ray (dashed lines) and gammas are shown.
However, if you select the sub menu, to the right of the color select (see the circled in the below image),
you can select to see alpha energies, beta endpoints, true-coincidence sums (i.e., when two gammas are emitted at nearly same time, so may be summed by the detector), as well as a few other options.
<div style="padding-top: 1px" align="center">
<img src="InterSpec_resources/static_text/images/ref_gamma_lines_sub_menu.png"  class="imageBorder" style="max-width:45%;" />
</div>
</p>

<p>
To show reference lines for multiple nuclides at once:
<ol>
  <li>Enter first nuclide, and adjust all options (shielding, age, DRF).</li>
  <li>Click the &quot;<em>Add Another</em>&quot; button, at which point the nuclide
    field will be cleared of the current nuclide; however the first nuclides lines will
    still be showing on the spectrum</li>
  <li>Enter the second nuclide and adjust all options.  Lines for both nuclides
    will be showing on the spectrum, but the tools table will only show values for
    the most recently entered spectrum.
  </li>
  <li>Click &quot;<em>Add Another</em>&quot;, and repeat for all wanted nuclides.</li>
  <li>Click the &quot;<em>Clear</em>&quot; button to remove the lines for all nuclides.</li>
</ol>

</p>

<div align="center">
<h2 id="available_srcs"><b>Sources Available To Display</b></h2>
</div>
<div>

In addition to displaying gammas for any non-stable nuclide, you can also display:
<ul>
</ul>

</div>

</div>
